<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The marrow of Christianity, or, A spirituall discovery of some principles of truth meet to be knowne of all the saints : represented in ten sections / by T. Collier ; whereunto is added an epistle, written by M. Saltmarsh.</title>
            <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C5292</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11073134</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11073134</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46231</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46231)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1420:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The marrow of Christianity, or, A spirituall discovery of some principles of truth meet to be knowne of all the saints : represented in ten sections / by T. Collier ; whereunto is added an epistle, written by M. Saltmarsh.</title>
                  <author>Collier, Thomas, fl. 1691.</author>
                  <author>Saltmarsh, M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 112 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Sumptner for Giles Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages cropped and stained with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theology.</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46231:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46231:1"/>
            <p>THE MARROVV OF CHRISTIANITY OR A ſpirituall diſcovery of ſome Principles of Truth; meet to be knowne of all the Saints repreſented in ten <hi>SECTIONS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By T. Collier, Minister of the Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added an Epiſtle, written by M. SALTMARSH.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 32.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed are ye that ſow beſides all waters, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſay 33.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He ſhall dwell on high, his place of defence ſhall be the munitions of Rocks, bread ſhall be given him, his waters ſhall be ſure </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>verſe 17.</hi>
                  </bibl> and thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his beauty, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Sumptner</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black ſpread Eagle, neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46231:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46231:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOr to thee alone do I commend this ſmal Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, who alone, art able to judge of ſpirituall things; for, the ſpirituall man judgeth all things. I have here in this Treatiſe, preſented unto publike view, ſome principles of truth. Although I ſuppoſe that ſome particulars herein, may ſeem ſomewhat ſtrange at the firſt ſight, yet I queſtion not, but the ſame ſpirit of Truth which is given forth from the Father through the Son to the Sts. will by degrees ſo gather us up into the myſtery of Truth, that we ſhall all ſpeak the ſame thing, from our walking in the ſame light, and acting in the ſame power, I have in this place only three words to mind thee of, as a preparative to what thou ſhalt read in this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the diſcovery of the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> to be but a humane man: a man, indued with humane perfections; is not a ſtrange, but a glorious truth, and meet to be known for, the knowledge of this one particular, leads us to the knowledge of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures nothingneſſe, the wiſdome, power, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; &amp;c. of the Creature, it is all but of the Earth; and that it is the proper work of Chriſt, the ſecond man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to ruine and deſtroy in thee, all, that is of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> even thoſe reliques that remaine; that wiſdom is turned into folly that ſtrength, into weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; that righteouſneſſe and holineſſe; into meere filthineſſe and pollution, ſo that Chriſt doth not where he comes in mercy, reſtore man to his firſt condition, as it was in <hi>Adam;</hi> but deſtroyes thoſe principles, as we are Chriſtians, and ſo creates a
<pb facs="tcp:46231:3"/>new man in us, which, after God, is created in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and true holineſſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24. and he that is in Chriſt, is a new Creature, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. All old things are done away, behold all things are become new; and as is the earthly, ſuch are they who are earthly; as is the heavenly (that is, Chriſt) ſuch are they who are heavenly, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.48.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the glory of a Chriſtians life is in the knowledge of Chriſt living in him: ſo the Apoſte <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. I am crucified with Chriſt; Nevertheleſſe, I live yet not I, but Chriſt liveth in me, and Chriſt in you: the hope of glory, is the great myſtery of the Goſpel for the Saints to know, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. that is, not to live wholly on the eying of what Chriſt hath done, without us for us; but likewiſe to be able to experience the life of that Chriſt in us, being made partaker of the ſame ſpirit, of the ſame Anointings, &amp;c. Thirdly, that the knowledge of Antichriſt, is the knowledge of a myſtery, I mean, a myſtery of Iniquity, which none can know, but thoſe enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from above: that, as the myſtery of the Goſpel is hid; ſo likewiſe is the myſtery of Iniquity hid from them that periſh.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, and in a word; my deſire is, that, what truth thou findeſt here written, thy ſpirit may be made one, in and with the ſame truth; that ſo, both thou and I, may have communion and fellowſhip with the ſpirit in the ſame truth, and what information and conſolation thy ſpirit findeth from what is truth (letting any Creature-weakneſſe, thou findeſt paſſe) let God have the glory, and ſo thy poore friend in the unity of truth, and fellowſhip of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:46231:3"/>
            <head>A Table of the principle things contained in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item>SECTION 1.
<list>
                     <item>OF <hi>Adams</hi> condition before his fall. <hi>Page 1</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adams</hi> in a condition of humane perfection. <hi>p. 1. 2.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Jmage of God, what in <hi>Adam p. 2. 3. 5.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mans beſt wiſdome, but the remainder of the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> in it, many too much glory. <hi>p. 3. 4.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What the Jmage of <hi>Adam</hi> is not. <hi>p. 8.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 2.
<list>
                     <item>The cauſe or ground of mans fall.</item>
                     <item>Firſt the mutability of his condition: <hi>p. 8.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>God not the cauſe of ſin. <hi>p. 10.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The ſecond cauſr of mars fall <hi>p. 11.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Satans temptation.</item>
                     <item>Why Satan called a, Serpent <hi>p. 12.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The cauſe of mans fall, diſobedience. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The tree of knowledge of good and evill. why ſo called. <hi>p. 13.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 3.
<list>
                     <item>Mans miſery by reaſon of his fall <hi>p. 14. 15.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Mans miſery conſidered under <hi>3</hi> heads <hi>p. 16.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 4.
<list>
                     <item>What is the means God hath appointed for the recovery of man out of this condition, that is Jeſus Chriſt <hi>p. 27</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The ſin and fault is layd upon Chriſt <hi>p. 17. 18</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Chriſt bare the ſins of all: all are ſaved, and how not ſaved; and the reaſon why. <hi>p. 19. 20. 21</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Chriſt not the efficient cauſe of love, but rather an effect of love. <hi>p. 22. 23. 25</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How Chriſt delivers from wrath. <hi>p. 13. 24.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:46231:4"/>
               <item>SECTION 5.
<list>
                     <item>How perſons come to have benefit by this means that God hath appointed, as the way of life; which is by Faith. <hi>p. 26.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What Faith is. <hi>p. 26. 27.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How Faith is obtained. <hi>p. 28.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith not a condition of the Covenant. <hi>p. 29.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith a branch of the Covenant. <hi>p. 3.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith an evidence of the Covenant. <hi>p. 30.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The means by which Faith is wrought. <hi>p. 31.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The properties and effects of Faith. <hi>p. 31.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>How Faith juſtifieth. <hi>p. 32. 33.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith produceth peace with God. <hi>p. 33</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Faith puts the ſoule into the poſſeſſion of love, it fills the ſoule with joy. <hi>p. 34.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 6.
<list>
                     <item>Wherein the condition of perſon reſtored by Chriſt, and their union with God, is diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: which is, firſt; a freedome from ſin. <hi>p. 35</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Second, in being one with, and in Chriſt. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Chriſt and the Chriſtians relations, one: firſt, Chriſt a Son; ſo the Saints. <hi>p. 36.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondly, relation of ſpirituall union. <hi>p. 37.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>In the ſpirit, power, wiſdom, righteouſneſſe love, and glory. <hi>p. 38.</hi> to the <hi>49.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Saints Communion with the Father, Son, and each other. <hi>p. 50. 51. 52</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 7.
<list>
                     <item>Wherein is declared what the Law is, &amp; what the Goſpell; with the difference between them, both in the Letter, and in the Spirit. <hi>p. 55.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:46231:4"/>
                     <item>Firſt, what the Law is, in the letter. <hi>p. 55. 56. 57</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Secondly, what the Law is in the Spirit. <hi>p 56.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What the Goſpell in the Letter is. <hi>p. 61. 62</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>What the Goſpell, in the Spirit is. <hi>p. 64.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Myſtery of the Goſpell, what. <hi>p. 65</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The life of Faith in the moſt ſpirituall. <hi>67. 68</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The difference between the Law and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. <hi>p. 70. 71.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The glorious effects of the knowledge of God in Spirits. <hi>p. 63.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 8.
<list>
                     <item>The matter of the Church, what. <hi>p. 75.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 9.
<list>
                     <item>The ſpirituall Kingdom of Chriſt in his Church in the latter dayes of the Goſpel, diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>p. 80.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Who are the ſubjects of Chriſts Kingdom, <hi>p. 81</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The externall glory of the Church of Chriſt in latter dayes. <hi>p. 82. 83</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The ſpirituall glory of the Church. <hi>p. 85.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The Kingdome of Chriſt wholly ſpirituall. <hi>p. 90</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Objections anſwered, conceruing the perſonall reigne of Chriſt. <hi>p. 93</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>SECTION 10.
<list>
                     <item>Of death, reſurrection, and Judgement. <hi>p. 108.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2. Part.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>A briefe diſcovery of Antichriſt or the man of ſin, both in the Hiſtory and in the Myſtery. <hi>p: 113;</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46231:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>PEruſing this Treatiſe, J could not but take notice of ſome pretious truths in it, and commend them abroad; The <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall deſigne</hi> of this <hi>Author I</hi> find to be this;<note place="margin">Rom. 14 17. Epheſ. 4.3. 2 Cor.</note> to ſet up the <hi>Kingdome of God</hi> in ſpirit, and to draw believers by <hi>that</hi> more into ſpirit, and that no difference of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adminiſtration, or <hi>Ordinances,</hi> ſhould divide Chriſtians that are baptiſed into one ſpirit; which truth J did much rejoyce to ſee from his <hi>Pen,</hi> and practiſe, and ſhould rejoyce to ſee the like from all the reſt. We know he is not a Jew, who is <hi>one outward,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> neither is <hi>that circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion which is outward in the fleſh, we are the circumciſion</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> who rejoyce <hi>in Chriſt Ieſus; and have no confidence</hi> in <hi>the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome excellent truthes <hi>hinted</hi> in this Book which I intend to ſpeak on, as of the two <hi>Adams<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the <hi>ſpirituall Church,</hi> the <hi>ſpirituall Liberty,</hi> the <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall,</hi> not perſonall <hi>reigne of Chriſt</hi>) in a little Treatiſe of my owne.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 2.</note> The Lord fill us with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>wiſdom and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation: The ſpiritual man</hi> judgeth all things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Saltmarſh</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:46231:5"/>
            <head>THE MARROVV OF CHRISTIANITY</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION 1. <hi>Of</hi> Adams <hi>Condition before his fall.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He condition of <hi>Adam</hi> in his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency before his fall, was 1. A condition of humane perfection, an upright and perfect man, this is the concluſion of wiſdome, <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 7.29. Loe, this only have I found that God hath made man upright, but they ſought out many inventions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But it is ſaid <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. that God created man in his own Image, in the Image of God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he him: therefore it ſeemes that <hi>Adam</hi> had more in him then perfect humanity, that he was made partaker of the divine nature.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:46231:6"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For the clearing of this Scripture, two things are to be conſidered. 1. what is meant by the Image of God? 2. what is not meant by it? 1. what we are to underſtand by the Image of God in which <hi>Adam</hi> was created: 1. reaſon, wiſdom and underſtanding, <hi>Adam</hi> was made a reaſonable wiſe and underſtanding man: in this particuler he was in the Image of God: A wiſe God; there is no ſearching of his underſtanding. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 40.28. <hi>Adam</hi> had the Image of Gods wiſdome, not the wiſdome of God, not the thing it ſelfe, it dwelled in God ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it was eſſential in him, but imparted to <hi>Adam,</hi> it was, and is in God eſſentially, he is wiſdome it ſelfe <hi>Adam</hi> was but the Image, God himſelfe the ſubſtance. That this Image was in man at firſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears firſt from Scripture, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.19.20. the Lord brought all the creation, to wit, ſenſitive Creatures before <hi>Adam</hi> that he might give names unto them, or to ſee what he would call them: God would now put him to the imploying of that reaſon and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding he had given unto him, a perfection of reaſon above all other Creatures. 2. It appeares from naturall experience, hence it is, that there is ſo much enquiring after a perfection of humane reaſon ſo much ſtudying of Arts, as <hi>Phyloſophy, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick Rhetorick</hi> &amp;c. but from theſe corrupted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques or principls of reaſon, yet remaining, in falne man, ſtriving after &amp; hardly being ſatisfied without the perfection of reaſon, able to give a reaſon of all thiings &amp; this your heathen <hi>Philoſophers</hi> have gon
<pb facs="tcp:46231:6"/>far in, this is that maybe attained in an high mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp; yet be but a reaſonable moral man, nay, were it poſſible to attaine that perfection that was in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> yet it would be no more then a morall &amp; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane perfection, and this is that which many who bear the name of Chriſtians to much preſſe after &amp; glory in, as if without this wiſdom there could be no knowledge of mind of Chriſt, thus did the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſeek after wiſdom. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. the <hi>Greeks</hi> being the deepeſt in the knowledge of humane Arts and of the nature and cauſe of things, therefore they would judge of the Goſpel according to reaſon they ſeek after natural wiſdom: but ſaith the Apoſtle, we preach Chriſt to the <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſhneſſe; ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is the Goſpel in the myſtery of it meer folly to the higheſt naturall underſtanding in the world, nay it is that which the wiſdome of the Goſpel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes where it comes, in power he deſtroyes the wiſdome of the wiſe, and brings to nought the underſtanding of the prudent, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. and here lyes the great myſtery of miſtake, I had almoſt ſaid, of Iniquity, we ſeek after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God unto this wiſdome of the firſt <hi>Adaem,</hi> how many are there that would confine the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God in the wiſdome, who are not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſay that <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> is the mother of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> &amp; without this naturall wiſdome men muſt com ſhort in the knowledge of God; when the truth is, the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was of the earth, earthly, the 2d. is the Lord from heaven, and they who have but the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> wiſdome are ſtil of the earth, earthly,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46231:7"/>the wiſdom of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> comes infinitly ſhort of bringing us to the knowledge of God in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but it is by the wiſdome of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> who is the Lord from heaven, and the wiſdome of the father, we attaine the knowledge of God in the ſpirit; which wiſdom deſtroyes, &amp; brings to nought the wiſdom of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. Chap. 2.6, 7, 8. and 3 Chap. 18.19.20.</p>
               <p>Note that all unbelievers and carnall profeſſors are in the wiſdom of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> all believers ſpiritually made alive by Jeſus being delivered from themſelves are in the wiſdome of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> the Lord Jeſus who is the wiſdome of the Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Adam</hi> was in the Image of God, that was in a perfect morall pure, and ſinleſſe condition, he was made upright, innocent without ſin, but he ſought out many inventions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How may a morall purity and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe be ſaid to be the Image of God?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. God was, and is perfectly, eſſentially, and ſpiritually pure, <hi>Adam</hi> was but the Image or Character of this purity, as it is poſſible to draw a compleat Image of Character of a living man in a peece of ſtone or timber, and we ſay and ſpeak tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is the Image or likeneſſe of a living man, yet it is not a living man, nor hath it any part of mans nature in him: even ſo was <hi>Adam</hi> in the Image of God, there was not onely the wiſdome of God in creating of him, but the properties of God
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46231:7"/>in ſome meaſure imparted to him, yet not partaker; of the divine nature, righteouſneſſe, and freedome from ſin was morally in him, yet not partaker of that ſpirituall holineſſe that is in God.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, and more principally in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> who was earthly, was the Image of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond who was the Lord from heaven, ſo that all the righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, wiſdom, &amp;c. of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> was but an Image of the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and that morall and humane perfection in the firſt, and thoſe remaining principles that yet remained in his nature was at the higheſt and yet it is but an Image, as a drawn Character in a peece of timber or ſtones of the ſecond; the ſpirituall and divine nature which dwelt in Chriſt bodily, and is communicated ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually unto all the ſpirituall poſterity of the Lord Jeſus, who in himſelfe and in his Saints is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this Image which was the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Adam</hi> was in the Image of God in reſpect of a power: he had power given him to ſtand or fall, and in this power he ſtood til the temptation came: the firſt temptation he fell, and this power was but an Image of the power of God in which the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> came, and of which all the Saints are made partakers, they injoy the ſubſtance of <hi>Adams</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Adam</hi> was in the Image of God in reſpect of eternity, he had given him an everlaſting being in that morall upright eſtate, had he not degenerated from it, as appeares <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17 In dying thou ſhalt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46231:8"/>dye, hence a negative muſt be neceſſarily inducted, in obeying thou ſhalt live, but this life in <hi>Adam</hi> was but a Character or Image of that ſpirituall &amp; eternall life, ſoules are made partakers of in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam, Iohn,</hi> 4.14. thus it appeares that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> was a man in whom all humane perfections, wiſdom, righteouſneſſe, and purity dwelt yet ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he was in a mutable and changable condition, and ſo quickly fell from his ſtation, and perfection in which he was created he ſought out many inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. A ſecond thing conſiderable, is what this Image is not?</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is not that wiſdome and underſtanding which the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> was indued with, and all beleevers are made partakers of in the dayes of the Goſpell <hi>Eſa.</hi> 11.12.1 - <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is not that purity and righteouſneſſe which dwelt in the Lord Jeſus the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo ſpiritually in all the ſaints, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither was it that power put in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> who is one in God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſtands while God ſtands, for he is the Lord from heaven: neither that power ſaints are made partakers of who are one with God in Chriſt, and kept by the ſame power unto ſalvation, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. preſerved in Chriſt, <hi>Iude</hi> 1.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither was his eternity ſuch an eternity in which the ſaints are inverted a ſpirituall eternity, an eternity in God the Father and in the Son a glorious unconceiveable eternity, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16 11.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:46231:8"/>
2. As it was a condition of humane profection not of ſpirituall perfection, ſo it was a condition free from payne, and ſorrow, for he was free from ſin. &amp; ſo from ſorrow; his ſin brought in ſweat and ſorrow</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. 2.</hi> The cauſe or ground of mans falling.</head>
               <p>THe cauſe or ground of mans falling from his firſt eſtate may be conſidered under there par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulers 1. The mutability of his condition. 2. The temptation of Sathan. 3. His diſobedient acting, contrary to the revealed mind of God.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the mutability of his condition, he was created of God, though upright and perfect, yet ſubject to a change: the power being put in his own hand; the firſt opportunity preſented him, he falls, and (indeed) it could not be otherwiſe, he could not ſtand of himſelfe unleſſe he had been God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> If the mutability of <hi>Adams</hi> condition was the firſt cauſe of his fall; then it ſeemes that <hi>God</hi> himſelfe was the firſt cauſe of ſin, if <hi>God</hi> made man at firſt in that condition that he might fall, nay that he could not but fall, then <hi>God</hi> himſelfe ſeemes to be the firſt cauſe both of ſin and miſery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the firſt cauſe of all things is in <hi>God,</hi> he was before all things, he created all things, and all things live, and move in him, ann by him, and he worketh all things after the counſell of his own wil, yet 2. Although he be the firſt cauſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46231:9"/>of all created things, yet not of any evil that through degeneration, and Sathans temptation, flowes from thoſe beings: man in his firſt creation was good, but through his degeneration from it, he became e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſo that the evill was not in <hi>God</hi> but in man.</p>
               <p n="3">3. God having made man in ſuch a condition, man of himſelfe freely voluntarily, and rebelliouſly fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>God</hi> bringeth about his everlaſting purpoſe in rayſing up ſome in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> to a ſpirituall and everlaſting union with himſelfe, where they ſhall be for ever preſerved &amp; be kept by the power of <hi>God</hi> from falling: and others; (to wit) all unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers left in the nature of the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> and there he manifeſteth his Juſtice. 2. the cauſe of mans falling was the temptation of Sathan or the Serpent ſo he is called <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1. note firſt what Sathan is that tempts and overcomes man, 1. he is a ſpirituall enemy to mankinde, as appeares not only by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding of our firſt parents but the whole Scripture diſcovers as much; he goes about like a roaring Lyon, ſeeking whom he may devour, no ſooner was man created of <hi>God,</hi> but he ſeeks preſently to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour him, <hi>God</hi> having given forth Chriſt as a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he preſently ſets upon him likewiſe, to devoure him, if he could, and ſo in him all mankinde for ever <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. Thus you ſee Sathan is an adverſary to mankind, 2. Sathan or the devils, or the fallen Angells the Angels that fell ſeem to be many, <hi>Iud.</hi> 6. the Angells that kept not their firſt eſtate are reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in everlaſting Chaines under darkneſſe unto the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46231:9"/>Judgment of the great day, ſo there are many devils or ſpirits, as appears by the man poſſeſſed by the divell, when Chriſt asked his name, he anſwers my name is Legion, for we are many. 3. He is a lying &amp; delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Spirit, that oft-times transformes himſelfe into an Angell of light: hence it comes to paſſe, that he ſo deludes all the Sons and Daughters of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that they look upon all his workes of darkneſſe with delight and pleaſure: and oft-times it comes to paſſe, that he ſo farre transformes himſelfe into a ſon of light, that he deludes ſoules under the name of Chriſt, and when nothing leſſe then the name of a Chriſtian will ſerve, he, will be the Chriſt, or rather the Antichriſt to deceive ſoules, hence it comes to paſſe, when downe-right Papacy will not ſerve, he will turne himſelfe into a prelatical ſhape rather then looſe his rule and credit amongſt the ſons of men: if once Prelacy grow out of date, he can change him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into other ſhapes; if ten horns be too heavy to be born, he will be content to wear but two like a Lamb, rather then none at all.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Why is Satan called a Serpent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe in his firſt prevailing with that woman he did either make uſe of the Serpent <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1. who was a Subtill creature, and ſo comes in the Serpent unto the woman, or elſe ſecondly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes himſelfe in the ſhape and forme of the Serpent and ſo repreſents himſelfe unto the woman, and ſo from hence received the denomination of a Serpent <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.9. In the firſt, then learne, that Satan uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb facs="tcp:46231:10"/>makes uſe of the wiſeſt and ſubtileſt creatures to bring to paſſe his will in or by them: if the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond learn that Satan can transforme himſelfe into any ſhape or forme to delude and deceive ſoules.</p>
               <p>A third cauſe of mans fall; was, diſobedient acting, contrary to the mind of God, <hi>In the day thou Eateſt ihereof, thou ſhalt dye,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Adam</hi> eateth thereof, and dieth: diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence was the cauſe of mans fall <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What was <hi>Adams</hi> diſobedience?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> Eating the forbidden fruit. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> What was this fruit?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The fruit of a Tree in the Garden or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2: 9.16: called the Tree of knowledge of good and evill: good, if a man did not eate of it; evill, if he did eat of it. A Tree, who ſo eateth the fruit thereof, ſhall know the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between good and evill; ſo he indeed knew good by the want of it, and evill by the ſence &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it: What myſtery might be preſented by this pleaſant fruit, I ſhall not at preſent diſpute, becauſe it is ſomething dark unto me; whether ſin which ſeems very pleaſant unto a carnal eye; or the world, which much prevailes upon a carnall mind; or honour, or both: All theſe temptations Satan made uſe of unto Chriſt himſelfe, and repreſented them to his eye, as a deceiveable fruit, if poſſible he might deceive him: And the Tree of Life repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Chriſt, that whoſoever eateth &amp; drinketh of him, might live for ever, <hi>Io.</hi> 4, 14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:46231:10"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION 6.</hi> Mans miſery by reaſon of his fall.</head>
               <p>MAns miſery by the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> was death, <hi>In dying thou ſhalt dy,</hi> or <hi>thou ſhalt dye the death, Gen.</hi> 2.17. Now under the name of <hi>Death,</hi> the Scriptures comprehend divers things: A ſpirituall death in ſin; ſo are all natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes,</hi> ſubject to externall miſeries, and deadly plagues, <hi>Exod.</hi> 10 17. Externall afflictions upon the body, ſo <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5.6 the diſſolution of mans externall and naturall ltfe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.18. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.4. The perdition of body and ſoule for ever: All which miſeries come in by the ſin of <hi>Adam.</hi> As the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Adam</hi> was the way letting in all good to mankind; ſo was the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> the way or floud-gate, letting in all miſeries upon foule and body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Some will object and ſay, But how could <hi>Adam</hi> loſe a ſpirituall life, and ſo come under a ſpirituall death? ſeeing he never had a ſpirituall life in God; how could he loſe that which he never had?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Although <hi>Adam</hi> had never a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall life in God, yet he had a ſpirituall ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting given him of God, free from ſin; and ſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of defilement: For the truth is, it is the
<pb facs="tcp:46231:11"/>internall part of man that ſins, the forme or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of man is acted by the guiding of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall part; ſo that Adam now dyes in his ſpirit, he hath neither power, wiſdome, nor will, to do that which is well-pleaſing to the Lord; he hath not only loſt that wiſdome, will, and power of acting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the firſt Adam; but likewiſe of believing, and ſo of applying that ſalvation ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the ſecond Adam, untill he ſpiritually and powerfully draw up the ſoule unto himſelfe, <hi>John</hi> 6.44. and ſo makes him not onely par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of all that compleat righteouſneſſe wrought for him; but likewiſe ſulfils all righteouſneſſe in him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.4. Or elſe mans miſery may be conſidered under theſe three heads.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A condition of death, as you have heard. <hi>In the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt dye the death;</hi> that is, death internall, and death ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, and death eternall; without a meanes, or a remedy preventing it. 2. A condition of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, <hi>I will put enmity between thee and the woman, &amp; between thy ſeed and her ſeed;</hi> &amp; all unbelievers, which ſo live and remaine, are in a ſtate of enmity, God hath not declared himſelfe any other unto them; and their nature is ſtill at enmity with God. 3. A condition of inſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to help themſelves: Adam was not able to help himſelfe, and all he could doe, was to hide himſelfe, he could not deliver himſelfe out
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46231:11"/>of this condition: neither are all the ſons and daughters of <hi>Adam</hi> able to help one ſoule our of this condition, if God help not. Therefore this ſhould teach ſoules made alive by Chriſt, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire mercy, and to cry <hi>Grace, Grace,</hi> un to the whole work of God, both in them, and for them</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> What is the meanes God hath appointed for the recovery of man out of this condition?</head>
               <p>THe meanes God hath appointed to deliver Man out of this condition, is Jeſus Chriſt; and therefore promiſeth Chriſt immediatly upon the Fall, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. Herein is Gods love manifeſted, that he leaves not man in his loſt eſtate; but gives forth his Son out of his boſome, that he might ſeek and ſave that which was loſt, and ſo deliver us from wrath to come, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. He is Jeſus the Saviour, and the alone Saviour of his people from their ſins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. <hi>acts</hi> 4.12. that is, he is the alone way, through which the Father brings downe ſalvation to ſinners, and through which he drawes up ſoules to himſelfe; there is no other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46231:12"/>way of God, down to the ſoule, nor of the ſoule, up to God, but through Jeſus, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> What muſt Chriſt Ieſus undertake and performe; before the breach is made up, and faln man recovered?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. He muſt take the ſinne and fault upon himſelfe, <hi>Iſai</hi> 53.6. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. <hi>He that knew no ſin was made ſin for us, that we might be made the righteouſnes of God in him</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. Admirable mercy! that when man had ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and loſt himſelfe; Jeſus Chriſt, who never knew ſin, either in act or thought, muſt now take upon him the ſinners ſin, and ſo be made as it were a lump of ſin, and this he did willingly of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he bare out ſins on his owne body on the Croſſe; Chriſt took the whole ſinne of Adam, and the whole world upon himſelfe, when <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned, and all mankind in him, Adam and all muſt have died, Chriſt takes the ſinne upon himſelfe; and ſo taking the ſinne upon himſelfe, he withall takes the curſe, and ſo undergoes the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death. The curſe was, <hi>In the day thou Eat eſt theroof, thou ſhalt dye the death.</hi> Chriſt he dies the death, that ſo he might free man from death; and ſo Chriſt in bearing the ſinne and the condemnation, recovers man out of this loſt and undone condition. Two objections here need to be cleared.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. Whether Chriſt Jeſus the Second
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46231:12"/>Adam bare the ſins, and ſo, the condemnation of all men?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, it is without queſtion, that he took the ſinne and fault of the firſt Adam upon him, and ſo the ſinne of the world, whoſe nature was in him, and ſo taking the ſin, ſo the condemnation of the whole upon him; elſe he could not have effected that work for which he came.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If Chriſt beare the ſin and condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all, why then are not all ſaved?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. All are, in one ſenſe, ſaved, that is, with an externall ſalvation from the preſent curſe and death pronounced, and ſo the whole world have a being by Chriſt, and a redemption, a ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, a peace, which it enjoyes by him; a mercy that they are not ſenſible of, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. <hi>having made peace by the blood of his Croſſe, by him to reconcile all things to himſelfe, whether things in heaven or things on earth, &amp;c.</hi> Note, all things are reconciled. What things? The ſame that were made by him, verſe 16. All things partake of this reconciliation and peace.</p>
               <p>Secondly, all are not ſaved with an eternall ſalvation, becauſe all do not believe. It is true, that there was a ſalvation purchaſed from the externall part of the preſent curſe for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſin; yet Adams poſterity acting other ſinnes, draw on other externall judgements; but there
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:46231:13"/>was likewiſe, by the taking away of the preſent judgement, or death threatned, a prevention of the preſent execution of that eternall death, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; and ſo a ſpirituall and an eternall life by Chriſt obtained; yet ſo, as that none partake, of it but believers: ſo that although there be a ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation purchaſed by Chriſt &amp; tendered unto all, yet none are made partakers of this ſalvation, but believers; and none can believe ſavingly, but thoſe who are drawne up to the Father, through the Sonne by a power above themſelves, who were known and beloved of God from everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Father giving forth his Son as a publick perſon, making ſatisfaction to the law of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, that all mankind might be brought under the tender of the Goſpell; that ſo, upon believing, they might be delivered from both the firſt Covenant, and tranſgreſſion, no man being (indeed) delivered from either, but by believing; all men remaining in the firſt Adam, and ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law of tranſgreſſion in the ſpririt, unleſſe believers; Chriſt having purchaſed an eternall ſalvation; but keeps it in his owne hand and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſeth it in the ſpirit, to thoſe to whom God gives hearts to receive both him and it: ſo now nothing hinders the ſalvation of any man, with relation to Chriſt, a Saviour or Deliverer from the tranſgreſſion and ſinne of the firſt Adam; (on Gods part) externally all partake of it; internally, onely believers; <hi>He is
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:46231:13"/>the Saviour of all, but eſpeacially of them that believe.</hi> And nothing (on Gods part) hinders the eternall ſalvation of all, with relation to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, or price paid, but only on Gods part, his eternall purpoſe to draw up ſome into union with himſelfe in his Sonne; and leaving others to believe, if they would, or could. And from hence, on the creatures part, being thus left, only a Chriſt tendered able to ſave them, if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, they being left of God, having neither will, skill nor power to believe, periſh everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, under the rejecting of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> It ſeemes to be injuſtice in God to condemne the ſin of all upon Chriſt, and yet to condemne it upon the ſinner too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. It was as eaſie for Chriſt, being thereunto appointed of the Father, to make ſatisfaction to the Law of Tranſgreſſion for the ſins of all, as one. Such was his excellent worth.</p>
               <p>Secondly the ſpirituall and eternall part of it remaines ſtill with God in Chriſt, and is handed forth to none but believers; and of it remaines that there is no injuſtice in God to put ſuch a worth in the ſufferings of his Sonne, that it is able to ſatisfie the Law of tranſgreſſion for all, and able to ſave all that come to God by him; and yet to condemne ſinne, even the ſinne of the firſt as well as the rejecting of the ſecond Adam, in all thoſe that refuſe him, ſeeing his eternal pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in all was, the ſetting forth of his Son as a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46231:14"/>maker that ſo there might be a viſible ground up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the beloved of God might accept of peace, and ſo come to enjoy that inviſible union with the Father in the ſpirit, which he from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity intended: and likewiſe, that there might be a viſible rule of rejecting all who wilfully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne their owne peace, and ſo judge themſelves unworthy of eternall life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Did Chriſt purchaſe life and love from the hand of the Father?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Nay, he did not purchaſe life and love from the hand of the Father, but was a gift flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth from the fathers love: the death of Chriſt was not the cauſe efficient either of life or love: but love in God was the efficient cauſe of the comming forth and ſuffering of Chriſt <hi>Ioh</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his ſon</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> In what ſenſe then may Chriſt be ſaid to deliver from wrath, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. And to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his Church with his bloud, <hi>acts</hi> 20.28?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. He delivers from wrath in a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold conſideration. Firſt, from that wrath and Juſtice of God, gone forth in a righteous Law it being broken, wrath is gone forth upon all, becauſe God is truth, and ſo in the Letter, wrath is gone forth upon all through Adams tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo all unbelievers in that ſenſe, are under wrath, and there remaine eternally if not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 3.2. They are delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:46231:14"/>from wrath with relation to their apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: never any ſoule comes ſavingly to Chriſt, but the firſt makes him ſenſible of an eſtate of Wrath, and ſo every believer may truly ſay, <hi>They were once Children of wrath,</hi> that is in an eſtate of wrath under the Law of Tranſgreſſion, and ſo are delivered from wrath to come; becauſe if God had not from everlaſting received them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the number of thoſe written in Heaven, they muſt likewiſe have endured wrath to come.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he purchaſed his Church with his blood; and ſo ſalvation for them under two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations: 1. He purchaſed his Church from the law of tranſgreſſion God having ſaid, <hi>in the day that thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt dye.</hi> Man eats and ſo ſhould have dyed eternally, had not God provided ſuch a remedy: therefore he gives his ſon to purchaſe Man from that condition. 2. He pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth His with his blood from wrath and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation in their own apprehenſions: man being ſenſible of his loſt condition, muſt have ſomething to ſatisfie his conſcience; therefore likewiſe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gives Chriſt, and in both theſe, not as the firſt and moving cauſe of any thing in God: but God out of his love gives forth his Son to effect that work. As if a man indebted for more then he is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver able to pay, the Creditor having vowed ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, the debtor is caſt downe and troubled exceedingly: the creditor to ſatisfie both his own
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:46231:15"/>word and the mind of the debtor: ſends forth his ſon, and fully inables him to pay the debt; he brings along the debtor with him, payes the debt, cancels the bonds and ſets him free; and thus it was with the Father, man had ſinned, God had ſaid in the day thou ſinneſt thou ſhalt dye, this debt of death muſt be diſcharged: the Father, that he might be juſt and yet a juſtifier, and that the conſcience of faln man whom he loved might be ſatisfied, he gives or ſends forth his Sonne, he payes the debt, and ſo ſatisfies the word of the Father, and the conſcience of the ſinner, and ſo (indeed) is not eſſentially the procuring cauſe of love, but rather an effect of love to ſatifie both the word of the Father, and the conſcience of the ſinner, and this was Gods way from eternity through which he intended to manifeſt hmſelfe to his people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:46231:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION V.</hi> How perſons come to have benefit by this meanes that God hath appointed as the way of life?</head>
               <p>SInners come to have benefit by Jeſus Chriſt, by believing, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16.36. He that believeth on the Son, hath life, and he that believeth not on the Son, ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of <hi>God</hi> abideth in him: Faith as an inſtrument is the meanes appointed of <hi>God</hi> by which, ſinners receive, and owne Jeſus Chriſt, and life by him. For clearing this truth, three things will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, what Faith is?</p>
               <p>Secondly, how it comes?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the properties and effects of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. What it is; Faith is the apprehending and applying Chriſt, and ſo the Father, and his everlaſting grace in him. 1. It is the apprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt that is the obſerving and behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, as he is in himſelfe, the ſeeing of him in his beauty, and excellency, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 33.17.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46231:16"/>thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his beauty, it is to ſee all that worth to be in him that the ſoule needes, and then 2. To apply him according to the ſoules preſent occaſion, a dying Chriſt to a dead ſoule, and this Chriſt commends unto us to be the faith by which Soules come to enjoy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.40. this is the will of him that ſent me, that he that ſeeth the Son, and believeth on him, may have everlaſting life, (note) Hee that ſeeth the Son, that is, apprehends that worth and excellency, that ability the Father hath put in him to ſave ſinners, able to ſave all thoſe to the utmoſt that come unto God by him, and beleeveth on him, that is applieth him, receiveth him as its alone Saviour, and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifier, to them he gives power to become the Sons of God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. even to as many as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve on his name. 3. This faith doth not onely apply Chriſt, as given forth of the Father ſingly, and a part from the Father, but it applyes, that is, ownes the Father in the Son, and that ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting love of the Father to the Soule, brought downe through the Son; for the Son is but the Fathers way downe to ſinners, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.6. <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.44. He that believeth on me, believeth not on me, but on him that ſent me that is, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not alone in Chriſt, but believes and injoyes that everlaſting good will and love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the ſoule, anb ſo ſeeth the Father in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:46231:16"/>Chriſt commending love, and ſo giving forth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the ſoule, and ſo is able to ſee and ſay that it is indeed God that juſtifies, and that God was in Chriſt, (as the way) reconciling ſinners to himſelfe, not imputing their ſins; and now the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſees that Chriſt never acted any thing, or brings downe any thing to the ſoule, but what was and is the good will and pleaſure of the Father, and ſo faith ownes, not only Chriſt, but the Father giving forth the ſonne as the price of their redemption, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. and way of their adoption, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How is this Faith obtained ?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is the free guift of God, as Chriſt who is its object and all other good things, for every good and perfect gift comes downe from the Father, God in Chriſt, is the Prince and Author of our faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. Looking to Jeſus the Author and finiſher of our faith, <hi>Eph</hi> 2.8. <hi>ye are ſaved freely by grace, through faith,</hi> &amp; that not of our ſelves, it is the gift of God; faith is the proper and peculiar guift of God, no man commeth unto me, except the Father which hath ſent me draw him it is the Father that workes all the Father firſt loves, and then gives his Sonne, and then drawes ſoules up unto himſelfe in the Son, elſe they never come: No man comes to me, unleſſe the Father draw him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6. hence it is, that the experienced ſoule deſires to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46231:17"/>drawn, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. for unto you it is given in the behalfe of Chriſt, not onely to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, but to ſuffer, that is, you who have received this gift of faith, muſt expect to ſuffer like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But is not faith held forth in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as the condition of the Covenant of grace, he that believeth ſhall be ſaved?</p>
               <p>Anſw. 1. Although it ſeemes in the letter of the Goſpel, to be held forth as a condition of the Covenant he that believeth ſhall be ſaved, yet it is in the ſpirit myſtery of the Goſpel, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition on Gods part, it is true, none can be ſaid and ſay truly himſelfe, that he is in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace, before faith; yet this faith is the gift of God, as you have heard, and if any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition it is on Gods part in the myſtery, and it is his promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. This is the Covenant I will make with them, I will write my Lawes, in their hearts, ſaith the Lord, that is, I will take them off themſelves, and make them partakers of my ſpirit, which ſhall cauſe them to own love in God, and to live out of themſelves, in God, and ſhall cauſe them to act ſpiritually, even as Jeſus Chriſt himſelfe acted, and ſo faith may be ſaid (indeed) to be rather a branch, or part of the Covenant of grace, then the condition, for God in the Covenant promiſeth to write his Law, and to give faith and all good unto the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46231:17"/>ſoule, he gives Chriſt a Covenant, and with him he gives all, having given us his Son, how ſhall be not with him give us all things?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Faith is indeed an evidence to the ſoule, that is in the Covenant of grace and made one with God, hence it is called, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. The evidence of things not ſeen, that is, not ſeen with a carnall eye, the ſpirit evidenceth it, and ſaith re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth that evidence, and ſo the ſoule is ſatisfied through faiths believing of the word and ſpirit of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> What is the meanes by which God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The meanes by which God workes faith, is, his word and ſpirit by the preaching of the Goſpel, as the inſtrumentall meanes of this ſpirit working as the principall meanes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14 <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.63. now it is true, God is not limited in his way of working, (that is) he hath not confined himſelfe to a verbal preaching, although it is true likewiſe, that he ordinarily and uſually worketh faith by ſuch meanes: but a Goſpell-preaching is of neceſſity in the working of faith; that is a ſpirituall Goſpel-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the love of God in Chriſt, and ſuch a preaching may be by the ſpirit of Chriſt in reading ſome word; or any other way he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to work, and it may truly be called a Goſpell-preaching: any ſpirituall Goſpel-diſcovery to a ſoule, through which it is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:46231:18"/>brought up into Goſpell-injoyments, may truly be called a ſpirituall unfolding or preaching of the Goſpell, hence it is, that the preaching of the Letter, or a verball preaching, is no where cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a powerfull and prevailing preaching, unleſſe the ſpirit preach: it is the ſpirit that muſt convince the World of ſin, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16. And our Goſpell came not onely in word, but in power and in the holy ſpirit. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. It is true, God uſually wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth by means, but it is as true that he can as well work ſpiritually without meanes, if he pleaſe; and this he hath done much of late, I do not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion but many who are ſpiritually inlightned, and live in the ſpirituall injoyments of God, have had experience of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> 3. What are the properties and effects of faith?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>An.</hi> The properties and effects of Faith are many; It juſtifies the ſoule from ſin, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.39. by him all that believe are juſtified from all things from which they could not be juſtified by the law of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu.</hi> How may faith be ſaid to juſtifie?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Not as the efficient cauſe of our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, that is, God onely in Chriſt, it is God that juſtifies who ſhall condemne?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:46231:18"/>
But 2. Faith juſtifies as it receives Chriſt and applyes him as its juſtification; ſo that it is ſaid to juſtifie, becauſe it ſatisfies and quiets the ſoule in Chriſt who is its juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. He that worketh not, but believeth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly, his faith is counted for righteouſnes. Note two words: 1. He that believeth on him that juſtifieth: that is, Chriſt all that believe, are juſtified by him, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.39. So it is Chriſt that juſtifieth; faith only ownes that juſtification held forth in Chriſt. 2. Word, <hi>His faith is counted for righteouſneſſe;</hi> that is either firſt, God never declares a man righteous and juſt, untill he gives him faith to enjoy his righteouſneſſe, in Chriſt: or elſe ſecondly, his faith is counted or called his righteouſneſſe, becauſe he never till then enjoyed his righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>And ſo that when I ſay, or the Scripture ſaith, that <hi>Faith juſtifieth:</hi> that is, faith receives and ownes the juſtification of God in Chriſt declared, and ſo ſoule by it lives in the injoyment of juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and freedome from ſin.</p>
               <p>The 2. property or effect of faith, is union and peace with God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Being juſtified by faith we have peace with God,</hi> ch. 15.13. <hi>Now the God, of hope filyou with joy &amp; peace through believing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is one glorious effect, that thoſe who once were a farre off, ſhould now be made nigh by
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:46231:19"/>the blood of Chriſt, and be brought into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it by believing.</p>
               <p>The third effect is, it puts the ſoule into the poſſeſſion of the love of God, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16. <hi>We have known &amp; believed the love that God hath to us: &amp; God is love, and he that dwelleth in love dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi> It acts the ſoule above it ſelfe and cauſeth it to dwel in God, and ſo to dwell in his love, and this is an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding glorious effects, and that which in the fourth place, fills the ſoule with joy. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.8. <hi>joy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable, and full of glory.</hi> What can a ſoule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire more, then to dwell continually in the love of God? When the ſoule is ſatisfied from its union with God, and its dwelling in God, that all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations and makings forth of God, is love unto it. And thus it dwels in love, and from hence is filled with joy, it cauſeth the ſoule alwayes to dwell at the right hand of God, where <hi>is joy &amp; pleaſure for ever more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, in a word to conclude, the effect of faith is ſuch, as that GOD by it workes up the ſoule to an internal and external conformity to Chriſt in ſome meaſure, with a ſpirituall and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal conformity in perfection in another world, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. where faith ſhall ceaſe, and love and unity be made perfect, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:46231:19"/>
               <head>SECTION <hi>VI.</hi> Wherein is the condition of perſons reſtored by Chriſt &amp; their union with God diſcovered?</head>
               <p>THe Reſtauration of perſons by Chriſt may be conſidered, 1. Either external and generall: or elſe 2. more ſpecial and ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>Firſt, externally and generally, and that hath a relation to all, it is as ye have heard formerly, 1. A condition of being in the world. 2. A conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of poſſibility of a ſpirituall and eternall wel-being in God, if God in his Sonne draw up the ſoule to himſelfe, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.44.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, and that I principally intend, is the more ſpeciall and ſpirituall condition of ſoules thus drawne up to God in Chriſt; it is not onely a reſtauration to the condition of the firſt Adam, with relation to a freedome from ſin. This every believer enjoyes by Chriſt, a freedome, a juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſinne. But ſecondly, every ſoule drawne up out of it ſelfe to God, is brought into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the ſecond Adam; which is a condition as far above the firſt, as the Heaven is above the Earth: For, the firſt man is above the earth, earthly;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:46231:20"/>
                  <hi>the ſecond man is the Lord from Heaven: and as all men have born the Image of the earthly; ſo thoſe who believe, beare the Image of the Heavenly; and as is the Heavenly, ſuch are all they that are heavenly,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47, 48, 49. And wherein in Chriſt exceeds the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> therein believers exceed; for they are as he is, even in this world, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>Now the condition of Chriſt. and ſo the Saints, exceeds the condition of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> not only in their being upheld by <hi>God:</hi> but principally, in theſe four particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In their ſpirituall relations unto <hi>God:</hi> Chriſt, and ſo all believers are related to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Sons, and that not only by creation, as the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> or naturall generation: but firſt Chriſt a Sonne by a ſpirituall proceeding and comming forth from the Father, who was eternally one in the Father, and ſo in him all believers are made by the ſame ſpirit, the adopted ſons of <hi>God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made partakers of the ſame divine Nature. <hi>Adams</hi> Son-ſhip was in the fleſh by creation, ours in the ſpirit by regeneration, and the ſpirit of adoption, which is indeed a myſtery to all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men, and worthy to be looked into and knowne of all the ſonnes and daughters of Syon, 1. John 3.1, 2, 3. <hi>Behold what manner of love is this that we ſhould be called the ſons of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:46231:20"/>
2. Relation of Chriſt, and ſo of the Saints as of ſons, ſo of a ſpiritual union with God, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a union by way of peaee, but a union of ſpirit: thus was the Father and the Son one, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.10.11. <hi>Ioh</hi> 10.30. <hi>I and the Father are one.</hi> And thus are all the Saints one in the Father &amp; the Son, and in and with each other in the ſpirit, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.21. It was a part of the prayer of Chriſt, who was heard in all things he asked, <hi>That they alſo may be one in us:</hi> Now the union of the Father, Sonne, and Saints may be conſidered, either as firſt a union of ſpirits; The Lord pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red down of his Spirit abundantly upon the Lord Jeſus, according to that Glorious propheſie, <hi>Eſay</hi> 11.2. <hi>And the ſpirit of the Lord ſhall reſt upon him, the ſpirit of wiſdom and underſtanding, the ſpirit of councell and might, the ſpirit of knowledge and the feare of the Lord.</hi> And this was fulfilled when Chriſt was haptized <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.22.23. Of this ſpirit are the Saints made partakers, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16.17. <q>I, ſaith Chriſt, will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Comforter, and he ſhall abide with you for ever even the ſpirit of truth, whom the world can not receive,</q> This ſpirit of Chriſt, or this ſpirituall anointing, is that which every ſon and daughter of God are made partakers of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.9. Now if any man have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is none of his, Chriſt dwells ſpiritually in all the Saints,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46231:21"/>Chriſt is in you, except ye be reprobates. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it concerns, all who profeſſe themſelves to be Chriſtians, to examine themſelves. It is much to be feared, that there are exceeding many car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Chriſtians, I meane, that beare the name of Chriſtians, and that in a more then a common and ordinary way. <hi>And if Chriſt be in you, Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>the body is dead becauſe of ſinne,</hi> that is, the body is a dead and ſinfull body, and cannot act toward God; &amp; if Chriſt be in you, you ſhall be ſenſible of it. Never a ſoule wherein Chriſt dwels, but is ſenſible of its owne deadneſſe, through the dwelling of Chriſt there, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.8. Ye are dead (ſaith the Apoſtle) and your life is hid with God in Chriſt: but the ſpirit is life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of righteouſneſſe, that ſpirit of Jeſus that adopteth ſons to the Father in him, and hath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered and made the ſoule partaker of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God in him: lives and acts conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in the ſpirituall Chriſtian. Hence it is, the Apoſtle could ſay by experience, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.20. I live, yet not I, but Chriſt lives in me: Thus are the Saints made partakers of the ſame ſpirit of life that was in Chriſt Jeſus, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. He that is joyned to the Lord is one ſpirit, of the ſame anointings, and the anointings that ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſhall teach you all things, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.27.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They that are joyned to the Lord, are made partakers of the ſame power: there is a union
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:46231:21"/>with the Father in his power, the ſpirit of might was powred upon Jeſus Chriſt, and he ſtood in the power of the Father: as he came forth in the wiſdome of the Father, ſo he acted by the power of the Father, and this power the firſt Adam never had, and as Chriſt the head was upheld in the Fathers power, he was anointed with the holy ſpirit and with power, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.38. All power in Heaven and Earth was given to him, ſo that he ſtood in the power and ſtrength of the Almighty (and this did not the firſt Adam, if hee had, then he had not fallen) he is called, <hi>Eſa</hi> 9. the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace, ſo that he ſtands while God ſtands; So likewiſe this is the condition of all the Saints, ſpiritually made one with God in him, the ſame power upholds them that upheld Chriſt, they are kept by the power of God unto ſalvation, Gods power is become the Saints power: A glorious word of comfort for the Sonnes and Daughters of Sion, with relation to afflictions, either externall or internall, they ſtand not in their owne ſtrength, they are not founded upon their owne bottome, they are out of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the power of God is theirs, and they may conclude with comfort, that while God ſtands, they ſhall ſtand, he hath promiſed to be with his in affliction, to uphold them, to comfort them, to carry them through in his boſome: If the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46231:22"/>Saints were but ſenſible of this truth, that the power of God is for them: it is that would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly help them againſt the feare of falling. 2. Conſider this might be a warning to the Saints, to take heed of acting in their owne power but in all undertakings to ſee themſelves acted by a power above themſelves.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As there is a union of ſpirits, a union of power; ſo there is a union in wiſdom, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God is become the Saints wiſdome, and that not as in the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> he was made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of wiſdome; God imparted wiſdome unto him, ſo as to make him a reaſonable man, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſdom according to his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: ſo that here dwelt in him, as you have heard formerly, a humane perfection in this particular: but the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> Chriſt, was not only made partaker of the gifts of wiſdome but he was the very wiſdom of the Father, hee was both the power and the wiſdome of God, he had the ſpir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of wiſdom powred downe upon him, hee dwelt in the Fathers hoſome, and lived in the knowledge of the whole Councel of GOD, and from hence he never did his owne will, but the will of the Father, and as Chriſt, ſo all the Saints are made one in this wiſdom, Chriſt who is the wiſdom of God is made unto us, wiſdome, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. not only by way of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, but by the operation of the ſame ſpirit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46231:22"/>who dwels as truly in every believer as in Chriſt, and as the wiſdom of the ſpirit increaſeth, ſo the wiſdome of the fleſh decreaſeth that wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was a humane wiſdome, this a ſpirituall and heavenly wiſdom, this wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome deſtroyes that wiſdom: that is, in the things of God, he deſtroyes the wiſdome of the wiſe, and brings to nought the underſtanding of the prudent: that wiſdome ſets the creature a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>working; this ſets the creature a believing: that wiſdom carryed on the creature in its owne power: this ſpirituall wiſdome ſets the creature out of himſelfe in the power of God: that wiſdom carryed on the creature to the anſwering of God in the Letter (and yet in all comes ſhort) this wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome carryes on the ſoule, where it dwells, not after the oldneſſe of the Letter, but after the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſpirit: in a word, that wiſdome could not help to the knowledge of God in the ſpirit: this doth, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. After that in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, the world (<hi>viz.</hi> in the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>) by wiſdome knew not <hi>God,</hi> but the wiſdom of Chriſt teacheth the ſpirituall knowledge of <hi>God,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12.14.15.16. Hence it is, that thoſe who are taught of <hi>God,</hi> deſpiſe the worlds wiſdome, and are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be fooles to the world, and in the worlds eyes, that they may be wiſe in <hi>God.</hi> Hence it is likewiſe, that ſo many ignorants, in the wiſe and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46231:23"/>learned mens account, are made partakers of the knowledge of God in the myſtery; which (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed) according to the word of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.27. confounds the wiſe and learned, and mighty things of the world: this being a truth, that Saints are made one in the wiſdome of the Father. How ſhould this, in the firſt place incourage them to look up to the Lord, for the more full enjoyment of this ſpirituall wiſdome? that as they are made one in the wiſdom of God ſo they might live in the ſame wiſdome: and from a deep ſenſe of their own folly, to look unto the Lord for continuall teachings, and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings forth in the ſpirit, expecting that promiſe to be fulfilled, Thou ſhalt heare a voice behind thee, ſaying; <hi>This is the way, walke in it, when thou turneſt to the right hand, or to the left.</hi> 2. This might be a ground of comfort to the Saints, in all their walkings with God: the wiſdome of God is theirs, that God, with, and in whom they are made one, is their wiſdome; and in the concluſion they ſhall be ſwallowed up in the perfection of it, as Chriſt himſelfe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.2. 3. This might anſwer that fooliſh opinion of they world, who look upon the moſt ſpirituall Saints, as the worſt fooles in the world: It is true, the wiſdom of God is folly with men; but if the could look with a ſpirituall eye, they ſhould ſee that thoſe people are the only wiſe people, wiſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:46231:23"/>in God, and thoſe who live below upon Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and things that will not, nor cannot ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, are (indeed) in Gods account the only fooles, and they themſelves ſhall be driven to confeſſe it one day. 4. Chriſt and the Saints are made one with God in righteouſneſſe; Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was Chriſts righteouſneſſe: for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the God-head dwelt in him bodily; He was filled with the ſpirituall in-dwellings of God; who continually acted him according to the divine pleaſure, and as the ſecond man was made one in the righteouſneſſe of the Father, ſo are all the Saints made one in the ſame righte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: he was made ſinne for us, that we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>might be made the righteouſneſſe of God in him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How may the Saints be ſaid to be the righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Either, Firſt in the Letter; there is a righteouſneſſe preſented, which is the firſt thing ſinners are made partakers of; that is, the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of a Chriſt, dying upon the Croſſe, making ſatisfaction to the letter of the Law, and to the conſcience troubled, by reaſon of that let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which is (indeed) the cauſe of ſin, for where no law is, there is no tranſgreſſion; Now, Chriſt dying upon the Croſſe, ſatisfies the Law; and likewiſe upon the ſight and application of him, ſatisfies the troubled conſcience. This is the firſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:46231:24"/>righteouſneſſe of God diſcovers to the ſoules of ſinners, and by faith makes them partakers of it, and this is called the righteouſneſſe of God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God gave forth his Son, inabled him to go through, and by his ſuffering, to obtaine ſuch a righteouſneſſe for his people, that might both ſatisfie the Law tranſgreſſed, and the Conſcience of mans tranſgreſſing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in the ſpirit, the Saints are made the righteouſneſſe of God; that is, God, now as in Chriſt, dwells and acts in the Saints by his Spirit, writes his Law in their hearts, makes them partakers of his owne nature, and ſo goes on in fulfilling his owne righteouſneſſe in them: For, the righteouſneſſe of the Law in the Spirit is fulfilled in us, as well as the Law in the Letter for us, who walke not alter the fleſh; that is, after the Law in the Letter, but after the ſpirit of Chriſt who dwels in us, and acts according to its own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and ſo by degrees drawes up the ſpirits of his people to himſelfe, untill at laſt, they are ſwallowed up in the fulneſſe, of the rigbteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God in the Spirit, and be made wholly and for ever one in the Father with Chriſt, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.2. A glorious myſterious truth, meet to be knowne of all ſpirituall Ones; this is the top of the Saints glory, and their height of ſpirituall perfection, the knowledge and enjoyment of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46231:24"/>this ſpirituall Oneneſſe in the Father, and in the ſonne, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.2, 4.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There is an Oneneſſe in love and delight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Father, Son, and Saints: the Fathers love and delight is in his Son, and Saints, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.17. <hi>This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi> well pleaſed with his Son, and with his Saints in his Son. Hence the Lord ſpeaking after the manner of men, is ſaid to delight and ſing and rejoyce over his people, even as the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome rejoyceth over the Bride <hi>Eſa</hi> 62.5. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17. to rejoyce even with joy and ſinging; So Likewiſe it is the delight and joy of the Saints to live in the Fathers love, the very thoughts of it is precious, and the injoyment of it, exceeding glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, though the ſoule ſeemes to come ſhort of the perfection of that injoyment in this world, yet what it ſees and injoyes, with the expectation of perfection in another world, fills the ſoule with joy unſpeakeable and full of glory; and now as the ſoule dwells in the Fathers love, delight, and joy; ſo likewiſe it dwels in the Fathers will, and it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights in, and is well pleaſed with the will of the Father, it can ſay with Chriſt what ever tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion preſents it ſelfe, <hi>yet not my will, but thy will be done,</hi> ſuch is the Oneneſſe betweene the Father, Sonne, and Saints, they delight and take pleaſure in each other.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There is a union in glory likewiſe; the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:46231:25"/>glory is the Sonnes glory, and the Sonnes glory is the Saints glory, what this glory ſhall be is unconceiveable and unexpreſſable, to go about to expreſſe it, either with tongue or pen, would rather darken it then illuſtrate it: yet a word by the way; the perfection of the Saints glory ſhall be the enjoyment of all things in God, who is, and ſhall be their everlaſting ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the ſpirit. Thoſe who dreame of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome after the fleſh, or of any externall pleaſures in the higheſt meaſure, diſcover themſelves, to have exceeding carnall thoughts of the Saints glory: It is true, they ſhall have a Kingdom, but a ſpiritual one, ſo called, becauſe injoying all ſpirituall ſatisfactions in the fountaine, when the body and all the whole internall and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall part of man ſhall be turned into ſpirit, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.44. <hi>And our vile body ſhall be changed &amp; made like his glorious body.</hi> In a word, Such is the Saints Glory, and ſhall be in the perfection of it, through their union with God in Chriſt; that we muſt conclude with 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.2. We are already the Sons of God; but it doth not yet ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare what we ſhall be, But this we know, when Chriſt ſhall appeare, we ſhall be made like unto him; and this is enough for us to know: And as there is an Oneneſſe betweene Father, Son, and Saints; ſo likewiſe there is a ſpirituall union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Saints: this was Chriſts prayer who was heard in all things he prayed for; that the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:46231:25"/>Saints might be one, as he himſelf was one, in, and with the Father: the union of the Saints, is not a carnall union, but a ſpirituall: they who are joyned to the Lord, are one Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. To encourage all the Saints to preſſe forward in the power of the Lord, after a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowledge and injoyment of this ſpiritual union with the Lord, and with the Saints; Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, friends, as this was not onely the reſolution of the Apoſtle himſelfe, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. but his prayer for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> 1.16, 17. That the God of our Lord Jeſus, the Father of glory, might give unto them the ſpirit of wiſdome, in the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of him, that their eyes being inlightned, they might know what was the hope of their calling, and the riches of his glorious inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the Saints: ſo is it my deſire, not onely to preſſe forward in the power of God, after the knowledge of this myſtery; but that all the Saints might live in the knowledge of it, that their hearts might be comforted together, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knit together in the ſpirit of unity and love. The effects of the knowledge of this bleſſed uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will prove exceeding glorious.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is that will produce a glorious ſpiritual communion, and fellowſhip, with the Father, Son, &amp; Saints; union alwaves being that which produceth communion, even a civil union with the fleſh: when once the Lord ſaith, concerning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:46231:26"/>man and woman, <hi>they are no more twaine, but one fleſh,</hi> that produceth fellowſhip and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion after the fleſh: ſo likewiſe, and much more doth a ſpirituall union produce a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all communion and fellowſhip; a fellowſhip and communion with the Father and the Son, in all his adminiſtrations, in all the wayes and acts of his providence, civill or ſpirituall: the ſpirituall Chriſtian injoyes God in all, 1. <hi>John</hi> 1.3. Our fellowſhip is with the Father, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt (Chriſt and the Saints from their union with each other.)</p>
               <p n="1">1. They dwell together in the ſpirit, they are his houſe, and he dwels in them; the Temples of the holy ſpirit, and they dwel in him: they who dwell in God, dwell in love.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They eat together in the ſpirit Eat, O friends; drinke, yea, drink abundantly; the Lord takes as it were ſpirituall ſatisfaction in his Saints, and they take ſpirituall ſatisfaction in the Lord; it is their life to live in the injoyment of him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They walke together in the ſpirit, they have their garden and galleries, and pleaſant delights.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They talke together, and commune with each other in the ſpirit, the Lord he makes forth himſelf in the ſpiritual diſcoveries of his love to his Saints, and then they are carried forth to tell him of it, to admire him in it, and to praiſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:46231:26"/>him for it: and thus there is many ſweet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and heart-diſcovery betwene the Lord, and a ſpirituall Chriſtian, which makes the ſoule to revive within it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Chriſt and the Saints lye down together in the ſpirit, and take their fill of love each with other, they ſleep, as it were, in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of each other, and ſo they reſt themſelves in love. And this likewiſe produceth fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip amongſt Saints, a fellowſhip in ſpiritualls, fellowſhip in temporalls, And they continued in the Apoſtles doctrine, and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in breaking bread and prayer, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bread from houſe to houſe, being filled with gladneſs and ſingleneſs of heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. And they who believed had all things common; a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity as well as a unity; that is, ſo far forth, as need is, &amp; calls for it; ſo in gifts, ſo in all things, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>All is yours, Paul, Apollo.</hi> and <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas:</hi> And Secondly, the knowledge of this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall glorious oneneſſe, which the Father pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced an exceeding earneſt deſire in the ſoule enjoying of it; to live more and more in that glory. What is the reaſon Profeſſors content themſelves to be ſo low, ſo carnal in their minds, but becauſe they were never acquainted with, nor enjoyed higher things? but the Apoſtle who had ſeen and taſted of that glory, forgets all behind, and preſſeth forward; if ſo be, that he might obtain the reſurrection of the dead, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46231:27"/>and apprehend that for which he was appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, that love, that grace, that God who had apprehended him. Certainly, that ſoul who hath once taſted how good, how gracious the Lord is, in the ſpirit, can never be ſatisfied with the knowledge of him, in the letter. 3. the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſpirituall union with God produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth an acting more in and after the ſpirit of God: How doth the creature ſet it ſelfe a works and acts it ſelfe even in the letter of the Goſpel, as well as formerly in the letter of the Law, for want of knowledg of the union in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power of the Lord, although without Chriſt, that is, not being acted by Chriſt; we can do nothing; the Creature being unacquainted with that ſpirituall myſticall union with God, acts himſelf in the things of God. 4. The know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this ſpirituall union with God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the killing and crucifying of that earthly part: nothing kills and deſtroyes the fleſh, but the rowing up in the ſpirit. Oh! how would the ſoule many times be content to undergoe any thing, ſo it might be rid of pride and ſelfe, and thoſe fleſhly corruptions, and why? it is the growing up in the ſpirit, that deſtroyes the fleſh: the more you live in and after the ſpirit, the leſſe after the fleſh. 5. It is that will help us to know Chriſt and the Saints, the more in and after the ſdirit, the leſs after the fleſh, and ſo will
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:46231:27"/>produce a more ſpirituall communion amongſt al the ſpirituall Saints of Jeſus. 6. And laſtly, it is that will make the thoughts of a change ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſweet, becauſe the ſoule lives in expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a glorious freedome, from ſin and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and a full perfection of ſpirituall and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory; therefore it can be contented to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt; whichs beſt of all, where it ſhal for ever live in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall admiration of, and glorying in the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall enjoyment of God, whoſe worke ſhall be everlaſtingly and fully to enjoy, and freely to ſing praiſes unto the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:46231:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VII.</hi> Wherein it declared what the Law is, and what the Goſpel is; with the difference between them both in the Letter, and in the Spirit.</head>
               <p>THE Law in the Letter is a rule of Life an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to thoſe moral principles of nature left in man ſince his fall; the ſubſtance of which Law, was written in the heart of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and was contained in that Verball word; <hi>In the day thou eateſt, thou ſhalt die the death.</hi> Man having yet the principles of that law remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in him, God having by the promiſed Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, given a farther being to mankind in the world, he gives forth the righteous Law more at large in the letter, that ſo his creatures might have a rule in the Letter, to walke by, and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might be the more ſenſible of the loſſe of both; that principle and power they had once in <hi>Adam,</hi> given unto them; and likewiſe with it given, though not the ſame power, yet the ſame promiſe of externall life in the Land, God gives them. 2. The Law was that by which ſin came: that is, by which ſin became ſinfull: For it is true, had not God given a Law; yet man would have been acting contrary to the pure mind of God: therefore he give a Law,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:46231:28"/>that ſin might become out of meaſure ſinfull, and it was added, becauſe of tranſgreſſion; for where no Law is, there is no tranſgreſſion: For by the Law, was the knowledge of ſin, and ſo it was an, adminiſtration of death, both in the hands of <hi>Adam,</hi> as well <hi>Moſes,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Law in the letter was an Image or Character of that ſpirituall righteouſneſs, God intended to bring in by Jeſus Chriſt: as <hi>Adam</hi> was an Image of that ſpirituall perfection God intended to make his partakers of in the ſpirit by Chriſt; So this Law in the letter was a rule anſwerable to that morall principle of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe in <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; a Character likewiſe of that ſpiritual righteouſnes that every believer attains in Chriſt: the righteouſnes of the law in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was not that believers injoy in Chriſt; but that righteouſneſſe <hi>Adam</hi> injoyed in his ſtate of innocency. It was not the righteouſnes of God; but a Character of that righteouſnes, holyneſs and purity, that all believers are made partakers of in the ſpirit: It was not that righteouſneſs, by which God intended to give life and glory eternally; but ſuch a righteouſneſs which had externall promiſes annexed unto it: For, if there had been a Law given, that could have given life; then righteouſneſs had been by the Law. Wherefore I conclude, that the Law in the letter
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:46231:29"/>was but a Character of the ſpirituall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, which is the life of the Saints, and that by which God never intended to juſtifie any to eternity: for the law in the letter kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, not juſtifieth; but the ſpirit giveth life, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. The law was given to <hi>Adam</hi> in the letter, and <hi>Moſes</hi> was the Miniſter of the law in the letter, but Chriſt is the Miniſter of the law in the ſpirit: Therefore <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith himſelfe, <hi>A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you, like unto me, him ſhall you heare in all things, Acts</hi> 3.22, 23, <hi>Deyt.</hi> 18.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> It is ſaid <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8. that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt was the Miniſter of Circumciſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, he was the miniſter of it for the truth of God, to confirm the promiſes made unto <hi>Abraham,</hi> he was a Miniſter of it, ſo as to fulfill the truth held forth in it: So the word Miniſter, <hi>(Diaconos)</hi> ſignifies, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving promiſed Chriſt to come of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> he gives forth circumciſion, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Ordinances, as Types repreſenting him, and he is the Miniſter of all, to act and fulfill all, and to be the ſubſtance of all thoſe Types for the truth of God: elſe God had not been true in his promiſes, neither had ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on been obtained either by the Fathers, to whom the promiſes were made; or the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:46231:29"/>who were a farr off, and likewiſe inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the promiſes; Therefore he was the Miniſter of circumciſion for the truth of God to confirm the promiſes unto the Fathers, and likewiſe that the Gentiles might glorifie God for his mercy: Not ſo much a Miniſter in the giving forth of it; but in the fulfilling of it, which gives occaſion to the Gentiles to rejoyce and praiſe the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj. Paul</hi> applyeth the words of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.12, 13, 14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 6, 7, 8. to be the righteouſneſſe of faith, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of faith ſpeaketh on this wiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true, that Chriſt and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Goſpel, was included in the Law. There was a literall or externall righteouſneſſe expreſſed in the letter, to which were exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall pall promiſes annexed: but there was a ſpirituall and internall righteouſneſſe included, which only beleevers were made partakers of, which was a righteouſneſſe brought in by Chriſt, and obtained by faith, which is the law in the ſpirit, or that ſpiritual righteouſneſſe of God, that beleevers are made partakers of, which is the ſecond thing propounded, what the law in the ſpirit is.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the law in the ſpirit, or the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall righteouſneſſe contained in the law, as you have already heard, is the righteouſneſſe of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:46231:30"/>God, which every believer is made partaker of. Note theſe two words for the more full clearing of it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that there wasa ſpirituall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe included myſtically in the letter of the Law, which none ever ſaw into; but thoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually enlightned. <hi>Paul</hi> had experience of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. <hi>For we know that the Law is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, but I am carnall:</hi> The Law in the letter was not ſpirituall: For the ſame Apoſtle could ſay, that he walked concerning the righteouſneſſe of the Law in the letter, <hi>blameleſſe, Phil.</hi> 3. yet he calls it a fleſhly walking: <hi>If any man had cauſe of glorifying in the fleſh, I much more.</hi> And he ſaith, <hi>he was alive ones without the Law; but when the Commandment came, ſin revived, and I died, Rom.</hi> 7.9. alive, without the law, in the letter: by that it was he judged himſelfe to be alive; he walked concerning that, blameleſſe; but when the Commandment came, that is, when the ſpiritual righteouſneſſe of the Law was unfolded, which was no leſſe then the righteouſneſſe of God; then he ſaw how ſhort he came of that righteouſneſſe: he was yet but in the letter, in the fleſh, and not in the ſpirit; <hi>Then ſin revived, I died.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, that this Law in the ſpirit, is that ſpirituall righteouſneſſe of God, that believers are made partakers of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>The letter kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:46231:30"/>but the ſpirit giveth life.</hi> The letter killeth, the letter requireth an exact and perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which none was able to performe; and ſo the very letter of the law did kill. So at firſt it killed <hi>Adam</hi> and all his poſterity, and ſo it kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Jewes, being given forth in a more large way; for it was the adminiſtration of death: but the ſpirit giveth life, <hi>viz.</hi> the Lord Jeſus, the ſpirit and ſubſtance of the law, both morall and ceremoniall; for <hi>the firſt man was made a living ſoule,</hi> to anſwer a morall righteouſneſſe; <hi>the ſecond was made a quickning ſpirit,</hi> to give life to thoſe, dead in the firſt <hi>Adam:</hi> And as the Father hath life in himſelfe, ſo hath he given to the Son to have life in himſelfe, and he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth whom he will, <hi>John</hi> 5. The Law in the letter killeth; the Law in the ſpirit quickneth: Therefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I came not to deſtroy, but to ſave, John</hi> 12.47.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what the Goſpel is, There is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Goſpel in the letter, and the Goſpel in the ſpirit: The Goſpel in the letter, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly doth ſignifie glad tidings; and this Goſpel is to go forth amongſt all; but none are made partakers of it in the ſpirit, but believers: All are made partakers of it in the letter, it is glad tidings to all, and that in a double ſenſe: 1. It is glad tidings to all; for all have a being by it: it is that which hath made peace for all; an exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall peace, in taking away that preſent curſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:46231:31"/>
Secondly, it is that wherein internall and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall peace is held forth and propounded to all, which is glad tidings; none are exempted in the letter, till they exempt themſelves through unbelief, and ſo judge themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of eternall life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, there is the Goſpell in the letter likewiſe, as it is a Goſpel of ſpirituall peace and reconciliation. And thus every believer receives it firſt in the letter, through the power of the ſpirit, and this is Chriſt in the fleſh, dying upon the croſſe, taking away the condemnation of the Law in the letter. And this is that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the guilt of ſin in the natural conſcience, a viſible ſatisfaction for a literall tranſgreſſion; This was Gods way to take away ſin, and this is the firſt diſcovery God makes of himſelfe to a ſinner, becauſe he is pleaſed to conform him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to that way that might beſt ſuit with our underſtanding, and ſo by degrees to draw us up more in the ſpirit unto himſelfe, and this is the Goſpell in the letter, anſwering the Law in the letter, and the conſcience troubled through the ſenſe of ſin, which is the firſt knowledge of Chriſt; and is (indeed) but a knowledge after the fleſh, and ſo is in the eſteem of the Apoſtle, but a carnall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (that is) being compared to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall knowledge: therefore the Apoſtle ſaith,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:46231:31"/>1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>I cannot write unto you as unto ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, but as unto Carnall, even as unto Babes in Chriſt.</hi> Note, I do not ſpeak thus of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt upon the Croſſe, and the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it, taking away the guilt of ſin, as a low and ſlight thing in it ſelfe: For firſt, it is Gods way to ſatisfie finning ſoules, and ſo none ever partake of mercy, but by this way. Secondly, it is that, being wrought by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt, brings ſoules under the denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of children, 1. <hi>John</hi> 2.12. Thirdly, it is that by which the ſoule injoyes much joy and peace; who ſo hath obtained it from the Lord, hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a good degree, and much boldneſs in the ſpirit. Yet fourthly, God uſually by this way, brings ſoules up into a ſpirituall union with himſelfe, and in compariſon of the ſoules in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying of God in Chriſt, the Scripture calls it <hi>a carnall or fleſhly knowledge:</hi> and doubtleſſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny may attaine the knowledge of the Goſpel in the letter, and may own a dying. Chriſt upon the Croſſe, and yet be but a humane faith, a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terall Goſpel, and never truly known in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. But thoſe who are brought to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of and believing in Chriſt dying upon the Croſs, by the ſaving worke of the ſpirit, ſhall grow up in the more ſpirituall knowledge of him,</p>
               <p>Secondly, the Goſpel in the ſpirit is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of God imparted in the ſpirit to the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:46231:32"/>believer: it is the making of the believer par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the ſame nature, of the ſame ſpirit that was in Chriſt Jeſus. The Goſpel in the ſpirit is the ſame as the Law in the ſpirit, and repreſents the ſpiritual righteouſneſs of God, with which he intends to cloath his people, and it is called, <hi>The righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. As there was a literall tranſgreſſion of the Law; ſo there is a Goſpel in the letter, to anſwer it; and a Chriſt dying upon the Croſſe. As there was a ſpirituall righteouſneſſe included in the Law, ſo likewiſe is there a ſpirituall righteouſneſs in the Goſpel, that is, in Chriſt, they are both in Chriſt: the former righteouſneſs is the knowledge of Chriſt, without, as dying, and ſatisfying: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, is the knowledge of Chriſt ſpiritually for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med is us, which is here done in part, and we ſhall in the concluſion, be wholly changed, and ſwallowed up in that ſpirituall righteouſneſſe. And indeed here lies the great myſterie of the Goſpel in theſe three particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God in Chriſt, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. 2. Chriſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually in the Saints, <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of glory, Col.</hi> 1.27.3. That full ſpiritual change in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſpirit at the laſt day, of the Goſpel in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, not onely that we are made one with God; but likewiſe that we are made one in God; he dwelleth in us, and we dwell in him, and we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:46231:32"/>now ſerve no longer in the oldneſs of the letter, that is, with our old nature, in the old letter, given forth <hi>Adam,</hi> and by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the old end, the obtaining of righteouſneſs, but in the newneſs of the ſpirit, that is the renewed mind by the ſpirit, to a new letter written in the heart to a new end, to glorifie the name of our Lord Jeſus, &amp; to declare our conformity to him in the ſpirit. That this is in the Goſpel, in the ſpirit, which the Lord Jeſus brings up his unto by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees; the Scriptures in the ſpiritual underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will declare, not onely for conformation, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19.20. In the firſt, the Apoſtle ſaith: <hi>Henceforth we know no man after the fleſh; yet, though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet henceforth we know him no more after the fleſh.</hi> Note, firſt there is a knowledge of Chriſt after the fleſh even of the Saints; <hi>Although we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet know we him no more.</hi> Why? v. 17. <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a new creature,</hi> Chriſt is formed in him af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſpirit, and he comes now to know a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Chriſt within him, as well as a fleſhly Chriſt without him. The 2d. Scripture faith, <hi>We have boldneſſe to enter into the holyeſt, by the blood of Chriſt, by a new and a living way, that he hath conſecrated for us through the veil;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>his fleſh:</hi> where likewiſe note, that the blood of Chriſt, is but the way into the holyeſt, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:46231:33"/>the fleſh of Chriſt is the veil, through which we enter into the holieſt, that is, into the ſpirituall and heavenly injoyment of God. We come firſt to the fleſh, and ſecondly to the ſpirit, the fleſh being the way to the ſpirituall injoyment of him, where Chriſt is entred already in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and will in concluſion draw all his ſpiritual Ones after him unto the ſame perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, into the ſame glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If this be the Goſpel in the ſpirit, to know Chriſt no more after the fleſh, and to live in the ſpirit, to looke upon Chriſt as the way, in the fleſh, into the ſpirit or holieſt where he is; then what need of faith ſo much ſpoken of in the Scripture, <hi>the juſt ſhall live by faith, and we are juſtified by faith,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Faith may be acted not onely on Chriſt dying upon the croſſe, but in Chriſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the ſoule: that is, my believing that Chriſt is ſpiritually formed in me; as well as that he hath dyed for me, that I am juſtified in the ſpirit, as well as in the fleſh; faith hath the ſame object in the ſpirit, as in the fleſh, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Chriſt lives ſpiritually in the ſoule, and that it ſhall be ſwallowed up in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, wholly in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. There may be often occaſions to make uſe of faith likewiſe, while we are in this body of fleſh: although the ſoule obtaines a good
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:46231:33"/>degree of the enjoyment of the ſpirit from, and in God; yet there will be through the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of corruption, ſome ſtirre and trouble; and this God in his wiſdome permits for ends beſt known to himſelfe. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who lived exceeding highly in the ſpirit, ſometimes in the third heaven, that is, in the higheſt dicovery of God; yet he meets with a thorn in the fleſh, the meſſenger of Satan to buffet him, that was, ſome ſtrong luſt in the fleſh, that might cauſe him to look down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: And the reaſon he renders, <hi>leſt he ſhould be exalted above meaſure,</hi> 2 Cor. 12. For, the truth is; if God ſhould cauſe any one to live alwayes in heaven; that is, above all luſts and corruptions, in the higheſt diſcovery and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God; hee would be ready to be lifted up above meaſure. Experience teacheth us as much, ready to look upon all knowledg and enjoyment, believe it to be nothing but carnall; therefore he brings down <hi>Paul,</hi> that he might exerciſe faith, and live upon grace as wel as others <hi>My grace is ſufficient for thee, my ſtrength ſhall be perfected in thy weaknes,</hi> So that notwithſtanding this life of a Chriſtian in the ſpirit; yet there will be the uſe of faith al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes either in the ſpirit, or in the Letter: ſometimes God brings a ſoule to live upon grace, as it was revealed by Chriſt in the fleſh
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:46231:34"/>and brought home and enjoyed by the ſpirit, when we are at home in the body, we are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from the Lord in the Spirit; but when we are abſent from the bodie, wee are at home in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There is a continuall uſe of faith, &amp; that of the moſt ſpirituall Chriſtian, with relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the perfection of our eternall enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: for the Saints doe not onely enjoy a oneneſs with God here, and from hence much ſpirituall and internall glory; but by faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, and hope expects that perfection of glory hereafter, wherein it ſhall be perfectly made like unto Chriſt, <hi>when this vile body ſhall be changed, &amp; made like unto his glorious bodie,</hi> which at preſent ſo acts it ſelfe even in the Saints, which prevents them even of that perfection of glory, which they by faith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect when the change comes: <hi>when corruption ſhall put on incorruption, and mort all ſhall put on immortality: when this naturall bodie ſhall become ſpirituall;</hi> then ſhall be fully enjoyed what hath been by faith believed, &amp; by hope expected; and of this hath the ſpirituall chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain a taſt by the ſpirituall enjoyment of God here, although not as then ſo fully ſwallowed up in that glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But it ſeems that Chriſt in the fleſh is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:46231:34"/>the way to Juſtification and glory, the way into the holyeſt, which is heaven it ſelf, <hi>where none ſhall enter till they are changed, but Chriſt who is entered already,</hi> Heb. 9.24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> True, Chriſt is entered into heaven It ſelfe only in perfection; but believers they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter likewiſe in part, <hi>viz.</hi> when they are got within the veil, that is to ſay, the fleſh; then they ſee into the ſpiritual myſtery &amp; manſions of glory unconceivable, and indeed un-utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, as the Apoſtle ſaith; and deſire to live continually within the veile, if it might be, while they are here, yet they are raiſed up more and more in the ſpirit: and in the concluſion, ſhall be for ever with Chriſt within all veiles, which was beſt of all; as the law in the Letter was a veil to the Goſpel, both in Letter and Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.14. So is the Goſpel in the fleſh a veil through which, and within which all the Saints by degrees ſhall fully enter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qu. What is the difference betweene the law and the Goſpel?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> The difference is both in the Letter, &amp; in the Spirit; the Goſpel in the ſpirit is the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that righteouſnes, ſpiritually included in the law, as the Type, Image, or character of that ſpirituall ſubſtance the Saints are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ekrs of. Hence it is often called the Law in the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46231:35"/>Spirit the Letter killeth, the Spirit giveth life, &amp; I through the Law am dead to the Law, that I might live unto God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.19. that is, I through the Law of the Spirit, that is, the righteouſneſſe of God in Chriſt, am dead to the Law in the Letter, that I might live unto God in the ſpirit, and not to the Law and ſelfe in the Letter.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Difference is in the Letter, of the Law, and ſo of the Goſpell, and this is glorious, for the Letter of the law requireth a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that was broken; death ſeiſeth on all by that meanes, the Goſpell in the Letter holds forth a righteouſneſſe in Chriſt, fulfilling the letter of the law, ſo that what righteouſneſſe is in the law required, is obtained by Chriſt, and every beleever is made partaker of it, and ſo the difference is, 1. The Law preſcribes a Rule, the Goſpell fulfills the Rule, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28, The law requires a righteouſneſſe, the Goſpell fulfills that righteouſneſſe. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. The law was the adminiſtration of death; the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, the adminiſtration of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Is not the law in the letter, a Rule to believers?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Not as it was handed forth by <hi>Moſes,</hi> from Mount <hi>Sinai:</hi> ſo it was a killing letter; but 2. as it was taken into the hand of Chriſt, and ſo ſatisfied and handed forth by
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:46231:35"/>Chriſt being turned into Goſpel-Rules; it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines a rule, ſo farr as we are in the fleſh, I meane, in the knowledge of Chriſt after the fleſh: but as God writes his Lawes in the hearts of his people, and taketh them up in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; ſo ſhall they live above the law in the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, even of the Goſpel; yet not without: for they have it within them: it is in their hearts, and ſo they are a law unto themſelves; Then the rule in the letter is as a ſtay in the hand, or as a guide in the way, helping the ſoule up to the Spirit, and then he walkes not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit, having the law of the ſpirit of life within him, guiding him in the way of holineſſe, and ſo that Scripture is made good, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. <hi>The anointings which you have received ſhall teach you all things, and ye need not that any man teach you: and the ſpirituall man judgeth all things, yet he himſelfe is judged of no man,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</p>
               <p>Application: To incourage the Saints in the power and ſpirit of Ieſus to preſſe forward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this knowledge, and injoyment of God in the ſpirit: this was <hi>Pauls</hi> reſolution, who had taſted of the ſpirituall diſcoveries of God (as deeply as any) to preſſe diſcoveries of God (as deeply as any) to preſſe forward after perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. <hi>Forgetting things that are behind, not alwayes living below.</hi> The effects of it will prove very glorious, 1. It is that by which you ſhal be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:46231:36"/>able with the more evidence of light &amp; truth, to judg of things that differ, the ſpirituall man judgeth all things. 2. It is that will make the life of a Chriſtian exceeding glorious, carrying him through all difficulties with much ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all joy. 3. It is that will put a period to all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and diviſions amongſt the Saints. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions flow from our ignorance, and dwelling ſo much in the letter, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Whereas there are among you diviſions and ſtrife, are ye not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and walk as men?</hi> Thoſe diviſions, and that ſtrife amongſt the Saints about things in the letter, argue that they are exceeding car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; but this knowledg of God in the Spirit, will as a mighty Gulfe ſwallow up all thoſe little differences, and put an end to all ſtrife, both among particular Saints, and in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. <hi>When once the mountain of the Lords houſe</hi> (which is his Saints) <hi>come to be establiſhed on the top of all Mountaines and Hills, that is, in the ſpirituall enjoyment of God, above all caruall and fleſhy things; then ſhall all warres and diviſions have an end, and not till then.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. It is that will cauſe many a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Starre to fall from Heaven: many who have acted much after the Letter, will upon the diſcoveries of the glory of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46231:36"/>God in the Spirit, fall from that light they ſeemed to have.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VIII.</hi> The matter of the Church, what?</head>
               <p>THE Church of Chriſt may be conſidered either as more generall, or more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. 1. More generall, and then it includes the whole body of the Saints in the ſpirit: This of ſome is called the inviſible Church; but to ſpeake in the Scripture-language, it may be rather called the generall or univerſal Church, the whol body of Saints in the ſpirit, called the myſtical body of Chriſt, becauſe of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall union with, and in Chriſt their head: This Church or aſſembly (for ſo the Greek <hi>Eccleſia</hi> properly ſignifieth) we ſhall read of <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23. Ye are come to Mount-<hi>Sion,</hi> &amp; unto the City of the living God, the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to an innumerable company of Angels, &amp; to the genearal Aſſembly or Church of the firſt born, and written in heaven, and to the ſpirits
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:46231:37"/>of juſt men made perfect; this is the Church that ſhall be made one in glory; the generall aſſembly of Saints, the ſpirits of juſt men, and it is that might be deſired at preſent, that Saints Communion might flow more from their union in the ſpirit, and not altogether from the union in the letter: this is the glorious Church of Chriſt; and the knowledge of it in the ſpirit wil cauſe Saints to own each other more in the ſpirit. 2. The Church of Chriſt may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered more particular, or a particular body, or company of Saints in the viſible profeſſion of the Goſpell, walking in the injoyment of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; taking particular care of each other, and building up each other in the faith, and of this Church we ſhall read, freqent in the new Teſtament; and this Church is likewiſe called the body of Chriſt 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 27. and it is not to be queſtioned, but that this practiſe is very commendable amongſt Saints: and the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God in the Spirit, and of Saints in the Spirit, will not breake or leſſen the fellowſhip of particular Churches, but increaſe it, and make it to be more ſpirituall: for, queſtionles that which tends to the breach of communion and fellowſhip amongſt Saints, is not God, for God is love: and they who dwell in God dwell in love: it is that will increaſe love, and this is the more excellent way, &amp; that which in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:46231:37"/>concluſion wil ſwallow up all differences: yet one thing is much to be deſired, that is, that there might be a generall union amogſt the Saints that thoſe who are ſpirituall might not be divided in the ſpirituall Communion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſome literall differences about the uſe of ordinances, and the like, Oh that the Lord would help us to beare with each other in ſuch things! why cannot Saints in the matters of difference beare with each other according to the Apoſtles rule? ſeeing he that obſerveth a day, obſerveth it to the Lord; and he that obſerveth not a day, obſerveth it not to the Lord, and both give God thankes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But our difference is in matters of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances for the moſt part which God commands, and hath given them to us as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True, yet they are ſuch commands and priviledges as God hath given to His ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to lead them up to himſelfe in the ſpiri: and what if ſome injoy God gloriouſly in the Spirit without theſe, and we find them ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and walking anſwerable to the ſpirit of Chriſt: why ſhould my conſcience judge another mans Liberty? and why ſhould not we hold communion with ſuch in the ſpirit and in the letter too, in thoſe things wherein there is a union? but the truth is, there is too
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:46231:38"/>too much erring at preſent upon both hands; the one judging it too carnall for any Saints to walk in the uſe of Ordinances, which is not a truth at preſent; the other judging it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Goſpel, and the ſtate of a Chriſtian to live without the practice and uſe of ordinances; a third ſort there are that would ſubmit to Ordinances, but want Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; and this is more carnall then either of the former, becauſe they expect that to bee in a creature which is only in God; but here ſhould be a bearing and forbearing where the Spirit of Chriſt is.</p>
               <p>A fourth ſort there are who put Ordinances upon thoſe not capable of them without any word at all in the letters, and this the moſt carnall work of all, and ſavours much of the earth, and of an Old Teſtament-ſpirit, from whence uſually the ground is brought: and it were much to be deſired that the Lord would be pleaſed to enlighten their eyes, that they might have more ſpiritual apprehenſion of the Goſpel, and the end of Goſpel-Ordinances; yet it ſhould be the wiſdome of the thoſe taught from above, to own any thing of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they find it: and although it is true, there cannot be a Communion with, and in thing a never of God preſcribed; yet the ſpirit of love ſhould ſo temper our ſpirits, as that we ſhould
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46231:38"/>not bite &amp; devour on eachother; but, that as many as are ſpiritual, though differing in ſome circumſtantiall things in the letter, yet owne each other in the Spirit, imputing thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences to the fleſh; and this union in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the knowledg of it, will in concluſion bring all the Saints into one ſpirituall way, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.9. And ſo they ſhall worſhip God in the Spirit with one heart, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. and ſo put an which flow meerly from the fleſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION IX.</hi> The ſpirituall Kingdom of Chriſt in his Church in the latter days of the Goſpel, diſcovered.</head>
               <p>THe Kingdom of Chriſt hath always beene and ſtill is ſpirituall; but in the latter days of the Goſpel it ſhall be much more ſpirituall and glorious than formerly, with relation to the ſubjects of it, for the clearing of this truth in hand, note theſe 4. particulars.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That Chriſt is a King.</item>
                  <item>2. Who are the ſubjects of this Kingdome.</item>
                  <item>3. That his Kingdom ſhall increaſe in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſpiritualneſſe in the latter dayes.</item>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:46231:39"/>
                  <item>4. That his Kingdome is ſpirituall, and not of this world.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt that Chriſt is King; I ſuppoſe it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable: all who own the Goſpell but in the letter, confeſſe as much in word; ſee a ſcripture or two to confirm it <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.6. the Lord ſpaking of Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon the holy Hill of Sion,</hi> notwithſtanding the rage of men, yet Chriſt is King, and wil reigne; ſo likewiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.8. but unto the Son he ſaith, <hi>Thy Throne, O God is forever, and ever;</hi> a Scepter of righteouſneſs is the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of thy Kingdome: he hath a Kingdome and a Scepture by which he rules; he is the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, a King of Kings, and Lord of Lords.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Who are the ſubjects of his Kingdome; it is true, he is King over all, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, he will rule over his enemies with his Iron rod, and daſh them to peeces like a Potters veſſel; but he is in a more ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner King over the Saints, and in them he lives; and ſo rules: in them as well as over them: he is not onely King of Nations, but King of Saints; <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. It is part of the Saints ſong of joy, juſt and true are thy wayes O thou King of Saints; and in the Saints he reignes ſpiritually &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully; for in the day of his power he maketh them a willing people: the Subjects of Chriſts
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:46231:39"/>Kingdome are a free people: the manner how Chriſt reignes in and over his people, and what are his Lawes, I paſſe it in this place, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr you to the Kingly Office of Chriſt in my booke intituled, the exaltation of Chriſt in his Offices: and ſo come to the 3. thing propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; That is, that the Kingdome of Chriſt ſhall increaſe in glory and ſpiritualneſs in the latter dayes: the glory of the Church in the latter dayes ſhall increaſe, and the manifeſtation of Chriſts Kingly power ſhall increaſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9. of the increaſe of his Government and Peace; there ſhall be no end. The Churches glory ſhall conſiſt of two partciulars, that is, externall and internall.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Externall, the Church ſhall injoy much externall glory, liberty, and peace, even in the world in the latter dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Wherein ſhall the externall glory of the Church conſiſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In the abundance of peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, even from the men of the World, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.12. I will extend peace to her, like a River, and the glory of the Gentiles like a flowing ſtream: peace ſhall be extended not onely in the ſpirit, but in the letter likewiſe; for the ground of this peace is rendred in. verſe 15, 16. for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Lord will come with fire, &amp;c. <hi>Eſae.</hi> 65.25. the Wolfe and the Lamb ſhal feed together,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:46231:40"/>&amp;c. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy Mountain, ſaith the Lord: God will take away the Wolviſh diſpoſition of men, that they ſhall live peaceably amongſt the Saints, they ſhall nor hurt nor deſtroy, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God will take off the ſpirits of evil men he will make them ſtoop, and fall before the Saints, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.16, 17. <hi>The Nations ſhall ſee and be confounded at all their might, they ſhall lay their hands upon their mouth, their eares ſhall be deaf, they ſhall lick the duſt like a Serpent, they ſhall move out of their holes like wormes of the earth; they ſhall be affraid of the Lord our God, &amp; ſhall feare becauſe of thee.</hi> Thus will the Lord deale with his enemies in the lattr dayes, hee will take away their Chariot-wheels, and cauſe them to drive heavily.</p>
               <p n="3">3, God will give the Saints a good name, even amongſt their enemies; they ſhall be high even in the thoughts of bad men, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.15. <hi>And ye</hi> (to wit, the Lords enemies) <hi>ſhall leave your name for a curſe to my choſen: for the Lord will ſlay thee, and call his ſervants by another name.</hi> Formerly, the Saints had a name of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach amongſt the wicked: if a man departed from iniquity, he made himſelf a prey; but the Lord will give his ſervants another name, even amongſt their enemies, that men ſhal not bleſs themſelves in their evill wayes; but who ſo
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:46231:40"/>bleſſeth himſelfe in the earth, bleſſeth himſelfe in he God of truth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. God will make his enemies in ſtead of perſecuting, to ſerve the Saints, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.12. <hi>For the Nation and Kingdom that will not ſerve thee, ſhall periſh; yea, thoſo Nations ſhall be ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly waſted.</hi> Ver. 14. <hi>The ſons of them that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted thee, ſhall come bending unto thee; and all they that deſpiſed thee, ſhall bow themſelves downe at the ſoles of thy feet, and ſhall call thee the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Lord.</hi> Thus you ſee the Churches ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall not onely acknowledg the Saints, and confeſſe them to be the Lords Citie, but bow down unto them, and do them ſervice.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Saints ſhall be exceeding many, and that will adde to their externall glory: Times have been, that to be a Chriſtian indeed, would have been a wonder, &amp; he that departed from iniquity, made himſelfe a prey, and ſo was counted the off-ſcouring of all things; but now a little one ſhall become a thouſand, and a ſmall one ſtrong Nation; yea, the Lord will haſten it in his time, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.22. and <hi>v.</hi> 5. Then ſhalt thou ſee and flow together, and thy heart ſhall feare, and be enlarged; becauſe the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Sea ſhall be converted unto thee, the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come unto thee. This, with much more, ſhall be the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall glory of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:46231:41"/>
Secondly, the Church ſhall enjoy abundance of internall glory in the latter dayes: both is coming on apace.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Wherein ſhall the Churches inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall glory conſiſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. In the abundance of ſpirituall light and knowledge: Much ignorance hath poſſeſſed the ſoules, even of Saints, a long time; a veil hath been ſpread over all Nations, both Gentile as well as Jew; but the veil ſhall be taken away <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25. <hi>And I will ſaith the Lord deſtroy or ſwallow up in this mountain</hi> (that is in the Church) <hi>the face of the covering caſt over all people, and the veil ſpread over all Nations.</hi> Such hath been the ignorance that hath overſpread all People, and Nations, through the ſpirituall operation of the man of ſinne; that the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Goſpel hath been hid, as it were from us, and ſealed up even with leaven ſeales, a perfection of darkneſſe, that none was found worthy to open; Humane Arts, and Creature-wiſdome being ſet a worke, did but ſo much the more darken it, and caſt a veil, till at laſt the Lord Jeſus begins to open it himſelfe, and will unſeale it by degrees, and cauſe the veil to vaniſh away, to the great glory of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Ones ; but to the great terror of all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts who were left without this ſpirituall knowledge of Chriſt. See the further confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this truth <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.9. <hi>The earth ſhall be
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:46231:41"/>full of the knowledge of the Lord as the waters co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Sea.</hi> As ignorance hath, as a veil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread over all Nations: ſo ſhall the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord goe forth aboundantly through out all Nations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.17.19, 20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.12, 23.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that which ſhall make for the Churches ſpirituall glory, ſhall be the injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a full freedome from the guilt of ſin; that which much troubles many a pretious ſoule: and it was that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was freed from, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>We have not received the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of bondage to feare againe; but the ſpirit of adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereby we cry Abba Father,</hi> And this is that the Lord hath promiſed to his people in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.24. <hi>And the inhabitants ſhall not ſay, I am ſick, the people that dwell therein, ſhall he forgive their iniquitie.</hi> Sin is the cauſe of ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſickneſſe. This cauſe ſhall be taken away: for <hi>they ſhall be forgiven their iniquitie, i.e,</hi> they ſhall live in the knowledge and injoyment of it, and from henceforth they ſhall not ſay. <hi>I am ſick, and the voyce of crying and weeping ſhall no more be heard in her, for, the former things are paſſed away: there ſhall be no more ſin nor ſorrow, but everlaſting joy ſhall be upon her head, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall paſſe away, Iſa.</hi> 35.10.</p>
               <p>A third thing that ſhall make for the Saints ſpirituall glory is the knowledge of, and injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:46231:42"/>of a ſpiritual Oneneſs with God in Chriſt and each with other; although this be a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirituall truth: yet it is that the Saints have lived exceeding ſhort in the knowledge of it, the knowledge and injoyment of it will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glorious to the ſpiritual chriſtian. What this union is, and wherein it conſiſts, I referr it to what hath been ſaid formerly in the glorious condition of perſons in the 2. <hi>Adam,</hi> above the firſt. A 4th. thing that will make for the Saints ſpirituall glory, is, a living above creatures and things, in the ſpirituall injoyment of God, whom to injoy is life; when all things below ſhall be nothing; when the ſoule ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſuffer the loſſe of all things, that Chriſt may be all <hi>and in all;</hi> the glorious Lord will be unto us a place of broad rivers and ſtreames wherein ſhall goe no <hi>Gally</hi> with <hi>Oares,</hi> nor ſhal gallant <hi>Ships</hi> paſs thereby, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.24. no need of rowing in creatures or things, no need of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant <hi>Ships</hi> of any thing to carry the ſoule up unto God, of to bring God in Chriſt, down to the ſoule; but the glorious Lord will be all, and in all, and the ſpiritual Chriſtian ſhall live in the injoyment of him, verſe 23 Then ſhall the tacklings be forſaken, or loſed, they could not ſtrengthen their Maſt, they ſhal not be able who deſire it to ſaile any further or longer in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, duties, creatures; but the great ſpoyle
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:46231:42"/>ſhall be devided, and the lame take the ſpoyle, the lame contemptable ones, they are the people that are like to enjoy this ſpirituall glory.</p>
               <p>A fifth thing that wil make for the Saints ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall glory, is a ſpiritual and internall confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity unto God: they ſhall live up in the ſpirit, and walke after the ſpirit, Chriſt will manifeſt himſelfe ſpiritually in them: the light of the Moon, ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of the Sun ſhall be ſeaven-fold as the light of ſeaven dayes; the light of the Moon, that is, of the Church, ſhall be as the light of the Sun, that is, Chriſt the Son of righteouſneſſe, who is both a Son and a ſheild; and the light of the Sun ſhall be ſeaven-fold, that is, Chriſt ſhall appear in the ſpirit to his, conforming them to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ſpirit, which will appeare ſeaven times more glorious, then formerly when we knew him after the fleſh, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.8. <hi>He that is weake and feeble amongſt them, ſhall ſhall be as David;</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſt; David</hi> ſhall be as God even as the Angels of God before him: This is the glorious conformity that all the Saints ſhall have unto Jeſus Chriſt in the ſpirit, and this glorious vnity and conformity unto the Law, of righteouſneſſe is that will appear at the firſt ſight of it very terrible and dreadfull to the ſons of men, <hi>Cant.</hi> 9. v. 10. <hi>Who is ſhee that looketh forth as the morning, faire as the Moon, clears as the Sunne, terrible as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:46231:43"/>with Banners,</hi> ſuch will be the ſtrangeneſſe of this glorious truth, that it will not onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear terrible and dreadfull to the men of this world, but even Chriſt ſets it forth himſelfe with a note of admiration, not as if it were ſtrange to him, but rather to diſcover her excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent glory; and (indeed) the Church will be worth a looking on, and her glory a ſeeking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of all ſpirituall ones.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Particular, propounded for the clearing of the truth in hand, is; that the Kingdom of Chriſt is wholly ſpirituall, and not of this world, that as formerly, ſo in the latter dayes, the glory of his Kingdome ſhall be in the ſpirit, and not in the fleſh; it will be ſpirituall, and not perſonal: for clearing of it, I ſhall firſt prove it from teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Scripture. Secondly, By ſpirituall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments grounded upon Scripture. Thirdly, Anſwer ſuch Queſtions and Scripture grounds, which ſeeme to hold it forth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By teſtimony from Scripture, it is the word of Chriſt himſelfe. <hi>My Kingdome is not of this world;</hi> that is, not a fleſhly, and externall Kingdom over the bodies of men; but a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and internall one, <hi>The Kingdome of Heaven is within you:</hi> So likewiſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5, 16. There is no more knowledge of Chriſt after the fleſh, they are too fleſhly thoughts for a ſpirituall Chriſtian. Secondly, it will appear by ſpirituall Arguments likewife.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:46231:43"/>
1. <hi>Argument.</hi> The ſpirituall preſence of Chriſt with his Saints, is the moſt glorious preſence. Chriſt will be moſt gloriouſly preſent with his people in the latter dayes, <hi>ergo,</hi> his preſence, and ſo his Kingdome, will be a ſpirituall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and not a perſonall. The Major Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is evident from Scripture, that the ſpiritual preſence of Chriſt, is the moſt glorious preſence: This Chriſt tells his Diſciples when he was perſonally with them, <hi>John</hi> 16.7. <hi>Nevertheleſs it expedient that I goe away, for if I goe not away, the Comforter will not come unto you:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Chriſt tells his Diſciples, <hi>John</hi> 14.26. <hi>That if they loved him, they would not reaſon, becauſe he ſaid, he would goe away;</hi> becauſe his ſpiritual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence was the moſt glorious preſence: &amp; we ſee it by experience, that the Diſciples of Chriſt were moſt ſpirituall, and had moſt ſpirituall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of God, when Chriſt was gone from them in perſon, and they enjoyed him in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. That the preſence of Chriſt in the latter dayes will be moſt glorious; appeares by all that have been formerly ſpoken, and I think none of light deny it: then the concluſion holds true, that the preſence of Chriſt with his people in the latter dayes, wherein they ſhall enjoy moſt light and glory; will be a ſpirituall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:46231:44"/>
2. <hi>Argument.</hi> If Jeſus Chriſt be known of the Saints no more after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit; then his regne in the latter dayes of the Goſpel will not be perſonall, but ſpirituall: but, he is no more to be known of the Saints after the fleſh, as you have formerly heard, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Therefore his preſence, ſo and his Kingdome wil not be a fleſhly or perſonall preſence and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but a ſpirituall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Argument.</hi> Spirituall glory, and ſpirituall enjoyment, is that which moſt of all ſuites with the Majeſty and glory of God. <hi>John</hi> 4.22, 23, 24. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.10.14. <hi>The glory of the Saints ſhall be ſpirituall, and their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment ſpirituall in the latter dayes; ſpirituall knowledge, Eſa.</hi> 11. <hi>and ſpirituall conformity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, Zach.</hi> 12.8. <hi>and ſpirituall joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, Eſa.</hi> 35.10, Ergo, <hi>the preſence and Kingdome of Chriſt, in, and with his Saints, will be a ſpirituall Kingdome, and not a perſonall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Ar.g.</hi> Chriſts Kingdome and preſence ſhall be with all his people, filling them with ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all glory, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 25.7. <hi>He ſhall take away the veil ſpread over all Nations, and v.</hi> 6. <hi>And they ſhall ſay, Loe, this is the Lord, we have waited for him,</hi> Chriſts perſonall preſence cannot be with all his at once: therefore his preſence and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome will be ſpirituall and not perſonall.</p>
               <p>Objections anſwered concering the perſonal reigne of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:46231:44"/>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. That Chriſt was promiſed to the Jews to come as a King, &amp; they to this day expect him to come as a King, to deliver them from their captivity. <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. It is is true, he was promiſed to come as a King, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.7. and ſo he came King, although not in outward appearance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Where is he that is borne King of the Jewes? we have ſeen his Star in the Eaſt, and are come to worſhip him.</hi> He was the King of the Jewes, when he was born, he was a Child, and yet a King. 2. he is King of all ſpirituall Jewes, <hi>For he is not a Jew, that is one outwardly, but he is a Jew, that is one inwardly:</hi> and Chriſt reignes ſpiritually in all his people, the Kingdome of Heaven is within you. 3. Chriſt will appeare a ſpirituall glorious King to the Jewes, the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the latter dayes, gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from among the Heathen, to himſelfe in the ſpirit, and ſo will reigne in and over them in the ſpirit gloriouſly, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: ſee ver. 24, 25. <hi>That they ſhall be gathered in with all the beloved of God, by the ſpirituall working of Chriſt,</hi> and not by his perſonall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing; is cleare from this ground: They ſhall be gathered unto Chriſt, from the beholding of Chriſt crucified, and not from the beholding of his glorious perſonall appearing: Therefore Chriſt ſhall come a King, in the ſpirit, to his people, and not in the fleſh: ſee <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10.
<pb facs="tcp:46231:45"/>
                  <hi>They ſhall looke upon him whom they have pierced, and mourn over him, &amp;c.</hi> The eying of a pierced Chriſt ſhall be the way of bringing in Jew, as well as Gentile.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. Chriſt ſuffered reproach and ſhame in the fleſh from his enemies: therefore, it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſhall be glorified in the fleſh before his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Chriſt ſhall without queſtion be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in the preſence of his adverſaries, and all Nations ſhall be gathered together before him, when he ſhall appeare from Heaven in flaming fire, to render vengeance to them that know not God, and obey not his Goſpel; but, whether Chriſt ſhall appeare perſonally, or in any perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall form, will be a great queſtion: but with much ſpirituall power manifeſting himſelfe to the ſalvation of his people, and to the confuſion of all his, and his Churches enemies, <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 3. It is ſaid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. That thoſe that had been beheaded for the teſtimony of Jeſus, and for the Word of God, that had not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Beaſt, nor his Image, nor received his mark in their fore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> heads, and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand yeares, and the reſt of the dead lived not againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For clearing the myſterie of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:46231:45"/>it will be requiſit, firſt to ſet downe the things aſſerted from hence. Secondly, to unfold the myſterie intended, which will anſwer the things aſſerted: the things aſſerted hence are theſe. 1. That Chriſt ſhall reigne a thouſand yeares perſonally. 2. That all the Saints departed from the beginning of the world, ſhall be raiſed, and come and reigne with him. 3. That the wicked ſhall not be raiſed, till after the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares be finiſhed.</p>
               <p>For anſwer unto, and clearing of the truth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. I conceive it to be a glorious truth, that Chriſt ſhall come and reigne a thouſand yeares, a long time, ſpiritually in his people; but not perſonally amongſt his people: that Chriſt ſhall reigne thus gloriouſly, ſee not onely this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>And the ſeventh Angell ſounded, and there weare great voyces in Heaven, ſaying the Kingdomes of this world are become the Kingdomes of our Lord. and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever.</hi> Thus, you ſee, Chriſt ſhall have a Kingdome, and for the time of it, it is ſaid <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. to be a 1000. yeares, and in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60. to be many Generations, <hi>I will make thee an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Excellencie, a joy of many Generations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> But its ſaid. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. <hi>That the Nations and Kingdomes of the world, are become the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever:</hi> therefore
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:46231:46"/>it ſeemes that his Kingdome ſhall be perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Nations and Kingdomes of the world, may be ſaid to be the Nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of Chriſt, in a two fold reſpect, and yet Chriſt not reigne perſonally; and this the Scripture clearly holds forth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the abundance ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted unto Chriſt in all Nations, that in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of what hath been formerly: the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Kingdomes, ſhall become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of Chriſt, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.19, 20.60. ch. from 5. to 12. verſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt may be ſaid to be the King of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in reſpect of the ruling of his Saints over their enemies, for in this Kingdome of Chriſt, ſhall the enemies of Chriſt be ſubjected, and ſhall ſerve the Saints, the Nations that will not ſerve thee ſhall periſh, and Chriſt reigning in his Saints over them, may be ſaid truly to reigne over them. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.7, 8, 9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26, 27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. Thus the firſt aſſertion in part is truth, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall reigne a thouſand yeares, that is many Generations; but it will be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and not perſonall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Aſſertion from thence is, that all the Saints from the beginning of the world, ſhall be raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and come and reigne with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:46231:46"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> For the clearing of the truth in this <hi>Scripture,</hi> which wil anſwer this aſſertion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, 1. what is meant by the behading for the witneſſe of Jeſus. 2. What is meant by not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the mark of the beaſt. 3. What is meant by being raiſed, living, and reigning with Chriſt. 4. What is meant by the not living of the reſt of the dead, untill the thouſand yeares were finiſhed. 1. What is meant by being beheaded for the witneſs of Jeſus: It is a ſpirituall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heading<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuch a beheading as all the Saints who ſhake off Antichriſts badge and yoake like to meet withall, Chriſt is ſaid to be the head of the Church, and the head of every man, that is, of every Saint, is Chriſt now; when the Lord diſcovers the evill of Antichriſtian wayes to his people, and they forſake it, they durſt not receive either the Image, name, or marke of the beaſt, they ſhall preſently be beheaded by the beaſt, that is, they will condemn them as thoſe that forſake Chriſt, and cry out unto them, that they are revolted, that they are Sectaries, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrits, Heritickes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And thus they behead the Saints ſpiritually, and that for the teſtimony of Jeſus, becauſe they cannot but declare the things that they have ſeen and heard from him, which will over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and ruine all things contrary to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46231:47"/>in the. 2. What is meant by a receiving of the Image or marke of the beaſt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> By the Image of the beaſt is meant that likeneſſe that it hath unto the firſt beaſt, who ſeemes to receive a deadly wound, being compared with Chap. 13.11. to 16. that is, this beaſt ſeemes to make a change, he ſpeakes great words, his looke is more ſtout then his fellows; he thinks to change times and Lawes yet when all is done, it is but the Image of the firſt beaſt, the exerciſe of the ſame power, the ſame wiſdom in the things of God, the ſame worſhip for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, it is all the ſame in ſubſtance, and it is but the number of a man all of the fleſh, it is from below, yet ſuch muſt the worth, and the excellency of it be for a time, that whoſoever will not receive the Image of the firſt beaſt, and account it ſomthing too, is likewiſe to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed, and not to be ſuffered either to buy or ſell amongſt them, and many a Saint is like to be given into his hand, and he ſhall prevail over them, but it ſhall be but for a time, times, and the dividing of a time, and then the Kingdome ſhall become the Saints. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.2. The Image is that internal ſpiritual principle from which the beaſt acts; for none can truly follow the beaſt, but thoſe who have received this Image, that is, who act from the ſame principl, e thoſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:46231:47"/>are acted, who act for and from the man of ſin, and it is called an image, becauſe it reſembles Chriſt, both in the internall as well as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall part; yet acts from his own wiſdome, by its own power, according to its own mind, to its own end, and this in all reſembles Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now theſe who refuſe this Image in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and cannot be contented with a wiſdome like Chriſt, a ſelfe-acting in the roome of Chriſt, a rule ſhort of Chriſt; and end beſides Chriſt: from hence caſting off this Image, is caerrid on in another track then before: they come to be beheaded for Chriſt, becauſe they cannot receive the Image, who is the Antichriſt in the ſpirit and not Chriſt, ſo that here is not onely the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of the firſt beaſt, with relation to patern and power, but likewiſe in relation to holineſs; the firſt will be for Chriſt, and ſo the ſecond, yet are both but Antichriſt. 2. What is meant by the marke of the beaſt in the forehead, and in the right hand; by the marke in the forehead, is meant the viſible profeſſion of Antichriſt in the externall part thoſe that would not viſibly profeſſe the wayes of Antichriſt: or in the right hand; that is, to act for him, theſe were denyed to buy or ſell, <hi>Chap.</hi> 13.17. to ſel, that is, to preach the Goſpel; for Antichriſt under the notion of preaching the Goſpell, ſells his wares, but a
<pb facs="tcp:46231:48"/>time is comeing, that none will buy their wares any more, ſo they deny any who own not the Image, name, or marke, to ſell; hence they may examine thoſe who preach upon ſuch and ſuch intergatories, and if it appear that they deny the Image, name or marke; they may not ſell, that is, give forth freely what God communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates unto them, when others ſel or buy, that is, partake of any ſpirituall good amongſt them, if they could prevent it, and thoſe were beheaded for the witneſſe of Jeſus, but they were at laſt raiſed and lived with Chriſt 1000. yeers, that is, raiſed up from their low condition, taken up into heaven in the ſight of their adverſaries, &amp; lived with Chriſt in the ſpirit, reigning trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly over all ſpirituall enemies, ſelfe, ſathan, world, and thoſe Merchants that ſell all (yea the ſoules of men too) ſhall be weeping and crying alas, alas, <hi>Rev,</hi> 18. when the Lord ſhall make good that word of truth, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.5. <hi>Heare the word of the Lord, yes that tremble at his word; your brethren that hated you, that beheaded you, that caſt you out for my names ſake, ſaid, let the Lord be glorified;</hi> that is, (it tends to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God to behead and to caſt out theſe men) but he ſhall appeare to your joy, you ſhall be raiſed up with Chriſt, and I will give you a new name, but they ſhall be aſhamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:46231:48"/>
                  <hi>Obj. John</hi> ſaith, the Saints that had not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Beaſt (he ſpeakes in the Preterplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectence, therefore it ſeemes not to be the Saints raiſed who at preſent were beheaded in the myſticall ſenſe, but the Saints that had been beheaded in the litterall ſenſe.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, it is the uſe of the ſpirit, or the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits Language, to deliver it ſelfe in darke and myſticall termes, ſo the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.5. that we which are alive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine till the coming of the Lord, &amp;c. the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeakes of, <hi>wee,</hi> as if he had intended the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> and Himſelfe, which was leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; but the Saints, who being all one in the ſpirit, and but one myſticall body in Chriſt, while there are any Saints in the world, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle makes it to be all one, as if he and the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> were them, and ſo delivers it in the preſent tenſe; when he might have ſaid ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to ſpeak after the manner of men, then they which ſhal be alive at his coming &amp;c. as in <hi>Rev.</hi> the word might have run thus; and ſo queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, it is to be underſtood: then they that were beheaded for the witneſs of Jeſus, were raiſed or lived, and reigned with Chriſt, as the ſenſe of the former; then they that ſhall be alive at the coming of the Lord, ſhall not prevent them which are aſleep: ſo that the ſpirit of God, might
<pb facs="tcp:46231:49"/>as well deliver a truth, which is in the Preſent tenſe, in the Preterpluperfect tenſe; as a truth in the Preſent tenſe, which was in the Future; and yet is, all to exerciſe the mind of him that readeth, and to let us know there is myſtery in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>Secondly, very few Saints have been behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the litterall ſence: thoſe that have dyed for Chriſt, have dyed other deaths, and not beheaded; therefore, we cannot underſtand it in the Letter, but in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p>The fourth particular propounded, was, what was meant, in that the reſt of the dead were not raiſed, untill the 1000. yeares were finiſhed; that is, none that had been bodily dead, Saints, or wicked, good or bad, were raiſed, till after the 1000. yeares were finiſhed, and then you ſhall ſee the reſurrection of all, which is called the ſecond reſurrection; the firſt is called a reſurrection, and the firſt reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; becauſe it ſhall be a reſurrection from ſhame and diſgrace in the world. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it ſhall be a glorious reſurrection in the ſpirit: this firſt, all the Saints have in ſome meaſure been partakers of it. Thus it appeares that Chriſt ſhall have a Kingdome, a glorious, a ſpirituall One.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But when ſhall this Kingdome be?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:46231:49"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is already begun in the ſpirits of Saints. <hi>The Kingdome of Heaven is within you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I beleeve that the time of the 1000 years which is a more glorious eſtate in the ſpirit is not yet begun: but the beginning of that time ſhall be when the 7. ſeales are fully opened, &amp;c. the 7. Trumpets fully ſounded, and the 7 vials powred forth, they being but effects of each other; the opening of the ſeales, occaſions the ſound of the Trumpets; the ſound of the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets occaſions the vials, the opening of the ſeales the unfolding of the myſteries of the Goſpell, (which have been hid, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.1, 2.) As light breaks forth, the Trumpets ſound, the ſervants of Jeſus preach forth the myſtery of the Goſpell, in the power and puritie of it, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions the vials of wrath to fall upon the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian eſtate, both in the ſpirit, and in the letter; which work is now adoing. (Wait the Lords time, and it will come on apace) But firſt, we are yet like to be given into the hands of the little horn, who changes times &amp; lawes; the two witneſſes are yet like to be ſlain, and to lye dead 3 dayes and a halfe; and the Woman cloathed with the Sun, to be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into the wildernes for a little ſpace, a time, times and halfe a time; the beaſt with two
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:46231:50"/>hornes like a Lambe, hath yet a little time to make uſe of his power; perſwading them that dwell in the earth, to make an Image to the firſt beaſt; and that none but thoſe who own it ſhall buy or ſell with them. the Saints behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the Alter to wait a little time, before they be raiſed up to live with Chriſt 1000. yeares: but it is not long, the viſion is for an appointed time: in the end, it will ſpeak and not lye; it will come, and not tarry: the firſt 1000. is almoſt paſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſecond and third, are coming on apace; and all the Nations and Kingdoms in the world, will come apace to be the Kingdoms of the Lord, and of his Chriſt, and he ſhall reigne for ever; their lives ſhall be prolonged for a ſeaſon, and a time; and other Scriptures are alleaged for a perſonall reign of Chriſt, as the ſtone cut out of the Mountain without hands, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. that is, the glorious power of Chriſt, by weak meanes, ſubduing al Antichriſtian enemies, without his Saints, &amp; all Antichriſtian things, by his ſpirit, within them: So that in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. the glorious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Saints attending on Chriſt in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, which ſhall be fulfilled at the raiſing of the two witneſſes up into Heaven, in the ſight of their enemies, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10, 11. This is the firſt glorious work of the Lord Jeſus, in, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Saints: the Lord reigneth, let the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:46231:50"/>Saints rejoyce: the Lord reigneth, let the world tremble, ſee <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.5. The Lord our God will come, and all the Saints with him, that is, Chriſt will come in the Spirit, and all the Saints ſhall appear gloriouſly in him.</p>
               <p>A word of application: Firſt, if this be truth, that the Kingdome of Chriſt is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Kingdome, and not of this world; this may inform us how farr, beſides the Goſpel in the ſpirit and truth of it, thoſe men are, who make the Kingdome of Chriſt to be meerely politicall and a ſtate-Kingdome, who turne the world by a humane power into the Church and Kingdome of Chriſt (as they ſay) and Chriſt muſt have a worldly carnall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, no better th n the Kings of the earth enjoy; or elſe he ſhall have none at all: it ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours exceedingly of the earth, and ere long thither it muſt returne. 2. This could incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the Saints to pres forward after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God in the ſpirit, that as the Kingdom of Chriſt is ſpirituall, and not of this world; ſo may the Saints Kingdome likewiſe be in the ſpirit; and ſo all their enioyments may be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall enjoyments: this is that will make the ſoule fat, and wel-liking in the Lord; Il fithe ſoule with joy and peace, which the world is not acquainted with; their eyes never ſaw it, nor their hearts conceived it; neither are they
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:46231:51"/>like to ſee it, unleſſe the Lord make them ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. X.</hi> Of Death, Reſurrection, Iudgement, and the ſtate of the Saints after Iudgemene, eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally with God.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, of death: It is appointed for all men once to dye; <hi>Duſt we are, &amp; to duſt we muſt returne;</hi> and therefore, it behoves us to to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it: All the dayes of mine appointed time, will I waite, til my change come: Death is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, although the time be uncertaine: it is, that none are in a common aid ordinary way ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from, unleſſe thoſe Saints who are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at the laſt comming of Chriſt; they ſhall be changed in a moment, in the twinkling of an eye, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51.52. and ſo ſhall be caught up in the ſpirit, to meet the Lord in the ayre, 1 Theſ. 4.17. Secondly, of the Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>That there ſhall be a reſurrection of the Body at the laſt day, is evident, <hi>John</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>John</hi> 11.24.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:46231:51"/>with 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. throughout <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12.13. although this truth is by ſome denyed, and by others, too carnally looked upon; ſome thinking, that our bodies of fleſh ſhall be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſame forme, in which it dyed, others that it ſhall be ſpiritual, yet queſtion whether it ſhall be of the ſame ſubſtance: therefore, it will be neceſſary, to conſider two particulars, for the clearing of it. Firſt, by what power we ſhall be raiſed, Secondly, with what bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>By what Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. By the ſame power, by which Jeſus Chriſt was raiſed; which was by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; ſpirit of God: he was declared to be the ſon of God with power by his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.4. Secondly, by the ſame power and ſpirit the Saints are inlightned ſelfe, which is the ſame power, by which the body of Chriſt was raiſed; ſo that when we ſay we are raiſed by the reſurrection of Chriſt in the ſpirit, that is, by the ſame power, by which Chriſt was raiſed: therefore the Apoſtle deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to know the power of the death, &amp; reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.10. by the ſame power and ſpirit ſhall our bodies be raiſed at
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:46231:52"/>the laſt day. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.13, 14 15, 16. this being a truth that they ſhall be raiſed by the ſame power: it may ſome what direct us to the forme in which they ſhall be raiſed, which is the ſecond particular, that is in a ſpirituall forme, not in a fleſhly for as the ſpirit of Chriſt raiſeth us up in the ſpirit while we are here, ſo ſhall it raiſe up our bodies in the ſpirit at the laſt day, it is ſowne a naturall body, it is raiſed a ſpirituall body; our vile bodies ſhall be changed and made like his glorieus body, he tooke upon him our form that ſo we might be brought into his form for when he ſhall appear we ſhall be made like unto him, the ſubſtance of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body raiſed in ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Of judgement it is appointed to all men once to dye but after this the judgement; when all men ſhall be called to an account before him (to wit, the Lord Jeſus) there to give an account for all things done in their bodies, whether good or bad <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. and ſo God in this way will acquit his Saints and clear them before the world, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this is not their life; neither that in which they appear <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.36. to 40.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, of the eſtate of the Saints after Judgement, it is firſt ever to be with the Lord, beholding his glory l <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.24. and in his preſence will be fullneſſe of joy, and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:46231:52"/>2. at his right hand everlaſtingly to be complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame glory, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. when Chriſt who is our life ſhall appear, we ſhall appear with him in glory, all fleſh ſhall be ſwallowed up in ſpirit, and our bodyes ſhall be changed, and made like his glorious body, all things that offend ſhall be done away, and we ſhall be made eternally one in the Father and in the Sonne, and in the Spirit one in eternity, one in injoyment, and one in glory this for the Saints is enough to know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, what ſhall be, we do not know, it is an height and debth, a length and breadth unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Oh the unſearchable riches of Chriſt! what the Saints do injoy, what they ſhall injoy, ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes up the ſpirituall Chriſtian in the beholding of it: hence let us continue ſearching after an higher meaſure of the height, depth, bredth, and length of his love, which paſſeth knowledge: and there ſhal we be able to ſee and ſay that <hi>his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is unſearch able, and his wayes paſt fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ont.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:46231:53"/>
            <head>A briefe diſcovery of Antichriſt, both in the Myſtery, and in the Hiſtory.</head>
            <byline>By <hi>THOMAS COLLIER.</hi> 1647.</byline>
            <list>
               <head>For my more cleare proceeding in the diſcovery of the Man of Sinne, five things are conſiderable.</head>
               <item>1 <hi>What Antichriſt, or the man of Sin is.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>What his Reigne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>What ſhall be his diſcovery.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>What his ruine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>When his ruine ſhall be.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION <hi>1.</hi> What Antichriſt, or the Man of ſin is?</head>
               <p>ANtichriſt or the Man of fin, is to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red either in the ſpirit, or in the Letter. 1. in the Spirit, Antichriſt ſignifies one ſeemingly for
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:46231:53"/>Chriſt, yet indeed is againſt him, and ſo is but a man of ſin, a Son of perdition, and this he will appear to be, both in the Myſtery, and in the Hiſtory.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the myſterie, or ſpirit, and in this he hath taken hold of every man, eſpecially in theſe latter dayes; yet tis true, much time hath been ſpent by many, to find out this man of ſin, who he is, and for the moſt part aſcribe it to ſome particular man, never looking at the myſtery, or root of iniquity, which is not in the firſt place, a man, but a wicked thing in man, and this, for want of a ſpirit of diſcerning, we have not ſeen Antichriſt in our ſelves, but have caſt him upon others, and ſo miſſe of the thing, or at leaſt, moſt ſtrike at the top boughes, and are ignorant of the root: Now Antichriſt in the myſtery, or ſpirituall and internall part; It is a confederacie between Sathan, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull heart of man, transforming himſelfe into an Angell of light: nay into the Sonne of Light; and while nothing leſſe then Chriſt, and Chriſtian wil ſatisfie; he will be the Chriſt, or at leaſt the Antichriſt, in ſtead of Chriſt to deceive ſoules.</p>
               <p>For this was and is the laſt, the greateſt and moſt deceiving ſtratagem that ever Satan made uſe of to ruin ſoules; that where he cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſoules but they muſt be Chriſtians, he can
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:46231:54"/>be content with that, ſo he may be the Chriſt: hence he is called the man of ſin, the Son of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, that wicked deceiver, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. It is not Satan acting in a carnall and filthy form of fleſh, but in the moſt refined part of the firſt Adam, ſo he keeps the creature in the firſt Adam ſtill, he cares not.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There muſt be a reformation that it ſhall injoy, provided it be legally in the Letter, it muſt believe or elſe it cannot be ſatisfied, and believe it doth; but the ground muſt be built upon that firſt: reformation qualification, &amp;c. wiſdom is required to walk in Gods wayes, and to the knowledge of the mind of God: wiſdom muſt and may be obtained; provided it be humane, the wiſdom of the firſt Adam that is enough: power of acting muſt likewiſe of neceſſity be obtained a power ſhall be obtained, but it muſt be a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-power, and a creature-acting under the name and notion of the power of God; that is indeed and in truth condemned though in name owned there muſt now ſometimes be a ſpirituall mind, and that injoyes likewiſe in its own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, although hardly obtained and indeed the higheſt pitch of ſpirituallneſſe is but carnall to the ſpirituall mans injoyment: this is a high pitch of ſpirituall mindedneſſe where Satan dwells; to have ſelfe thoughts
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:46231:54"/>of reformation, thoughts to pray more; to walke more exactly, and to pleaſe God better; never, thoughts of living out of its ſelfe more, and of living in the injoyment of God in the ſpirit more; and ſpirituall joy it muſt haue ſometimes too: why? that it ſhall have likewiſe, but it muſt ariſe from inlargement in duties, humiliations, ſelfe-actings, reformation and all from ſelfe, and thus Satan and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull heart joynes together to the deluſion of many a ſoule, and this is Antichriſtian in the myſterie; the man of ſinne ſpoken of in Scripture that comes with all deceiveableneſſe of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe: and well may be called a man of ſinne, an Antichriſt, a myſtery of iniquity; for in this ſhape he deceives ſoules, and they are never ſenſible of it, drawn in and never know it, until everlaſtingly undon, and he hath his diverſities of forms in this kind.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If the name of Chriſtian will ſerve, and yet live looſe and prophane; that they ſhall have and there he will hold them. If there muſt bee a conformity to CHRIST, and a more zealous and conſcionable walking; to quiet the conſcience, ſhal have it: he will go as neere unto Chriſt with the ſoule as may be; provided it reſt it ſelfe below: and thus, Chriſt ſaith many ſhall come under this deluſion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting life from duty, and it will apprear to be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:46231:55"/>but workes of iniquity of ſin, (why) becauſe acted by the man of ſinne, acted not from a right principle, nor by a right power, neither to a right end; acting there muſt be, but not Chriſt acting. Hence it is, that though he will be a Chriſtian, and ſo talkes much of Chriſt, yet, he denyes Chriſt to be come in the fleſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that is, in the fleſh of his Saints; the ſpirit of Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting and working all things in the Saints (and they are ſenſible of it) and thus this deceiveable man of ſinne carries on hood winkt to perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on many and many a ſoule. And now it is more wicked and deceiveable, then when in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place, acting after the luſts of the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.19 20.21. then every one almoſt is ſenſible of 1. Hence it is, that Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.45. The uncleane ſpirit being caſt out, that is, cut in its unclean form it can no longer be owned, he is now content to come in when it is ſwept &amp; garniſhed, prophaneſſe and filthineſſe is gone, and now be comes in a more refined forme, perhaps legall reformation, as the preſent Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees to whom Chriſt ſpake, or elſe the name of Chriſtian or the knowledge of Chriſt, after the fleſh; but Chriſt ſaith the latter end of the man thus deceived is ſeven times worſe then the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining; he comes in this refined form with ſeven worſe ſpirits then himſelf, and ſo makes him
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:46231:55"/>ſeven times more, the child of perdition than before. Oh then, how doth it concern every one bearing the name of Chriſtian to look about themſelves, if they are not deceived and deluded, with this Antichriſt under the name of Chriſt! ſeeing it is the high way of ſoules ruine, now in the dayes of the Goſpell; for herein doth Sathan declare himſelf to be the Maſter of arts in tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming himſelfe into the ſon of light, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of Chriſt, and Chriſtian to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ruine ſoules. 2. There is Antichriſt in the Hiſtory or in the Letter, and this flowes from Antichriſt in the Spirit: now the ſoule being poſſeſſed with Antichriſt, he growes up into ſome forme, and now not only in the ſpirit inviſibly, but in the letter: more viſible, hee appearee ſitting in the ſeat of God, and he may be deſcryed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally under theſe three heads, as ſitting in the ſeat of Chriſt, and acting thoſe things which properly belong to Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In making Chriſtians by a humane power, it being the proper worke of God in Chriſt to make Chriſtians; <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.37.44. but now here is Antichriſt will undertake the buſineſſe and ſo turnes the world into Chriſtians or rather Antichriſtians, and pretend that they doe the worke of Chriſt, too: when, if he did the worke of Chriſt, he would rather keep of all carnall ignorant ones, and accept of none,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:46231:56"/>untill made willing and ſpirituall by Jeſus Chriſt; for Chriſt doth not onely own ſoules when they come, but firſt gives them a will to come, and that by a ſpirituall, and not a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane power. Hence it comes to paſs, that there are ſo many carnall profane ones under the name of Chriſtian, becauſe made Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an not by Jeſus Chriſt, but by men.</p>
               <p>Oh that the Lord would be pleaſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the underſtandings of theſe men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that they might not walke in a way ſo directly oppoſit to the Goſpel, and deſtructive to their own and millions of ſoules.</p>
               <p>in preſcribing rules of worſhip which is properly onely to Jeſus Chriſt, to preſcribe rules, and 10 carry through the ſoule in acting according to theſe rules.</p>
               <p>To preſcribe rules; this belongs unto Chriſt, &amp; whoſoever undertakes it, puts themſelves in the roome of Chriſt, &amp; is the Antichriſt: this is to exerciſe-creature wiſdom in the things of Jeſus Chriſt and (indeed) to ſit in the ſeat of God it is the worke of Chriſt in the ſpirit to help in prayer or any duty; we know not what we pray for as we ought, but the ſpirit helpeth our infirmities <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. It is Chriſt that helpeth both to ſee our want, &amp; formeth by his ſpirit, words within accordingly. Therefore thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:46231:56"/>formes and rules of worſhip put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the roome of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It belongs to Chriſt to give in power to act according to thoſe rules, but Antichriſt gives the command, and ſo carries on an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall acting, and not according to Chriſt, but his owne mind.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Antichriſt may be diſcovered as ſitting in the ſeat of God, not onely, 1. In making Chriſtians, 2. In preſcribing rules, but 3. In compelling all unto thoſe rules whatever Chriſt ſaith, that matters not; he himſelfe will the Chriſt, and muſt be obeyed, let Chriſt ſay what he will, and all that queſtion his power, muſt be the Antichriſt, for he exalteth himſelfe above all that is called God, or that is worſhiped; ſo that he as God, ſitteth in the Temple of God; ſhewing himſelfe that he is God, and in all theſe particulars, there is a myſterie lyeth, a myſterie of iniquity, that is iniquity hid under the name and notion of Chriſt? therfore ſo much the more to be dreaded.</p>
               <p>To bea Chriſtian, is accounted agallant thing; and therefore, not himſelf only, but others like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, look upon it to be a matter of much pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety to make men Chriſtians and cauſe them to own Chriſt.</p>
               <p>On I but here lyes a myſtery of iniquity, many ſoules made Chriſtians by a humane
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:46231:57"/>power, are but Antichriſtians, and ſo under the name of Chriſtian, are likely to be undone for ever, if the Lord prevent it not: an excellent thing accounted in the world to make creaturs Chriſtians, as ſoone as they are borne, by ſprinckling a little water upon them, and ſo in bearing them in hand, that they are ſo ever after but here lyeth a myſtery of in quity, and one of the ſoule-running myſteries of iniquity as ever came from Hell: Speak <hi>England,</hi> ſpeak all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions called Chriſtian; whether (almoſt all people of all ſorts, devoutly ſlaine in the ſpirit under this myſtery of iniquity) to have formes of worſhips prescribed: that all Prieſts and People may walk in one forme and way of worſhip, and all compelled unto it; is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an excellent part of Chriſtianity? but here lyeth a myſtery of iniquity under it. Firſt, it brings all ſorts of people to be acting in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, though worſe then nothing, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude themſelves in all their actings; it cauſeth them to look to men, and not to Chriſt. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it cauſeth them to bleſſe themſelves in their unity, in formes and worſhips never queſtioning their Oneneſſe with Chriſt in the ſpirit, they are as ſtrangers unto it. Hence it is, that uniformity in the Letter, is ſo much called for amongſt all ſorts of People; being wholly ignorant of unity in ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:46231:57"/>
I could inſtance in divers other particulars, as Miniſtry, Guifts, Church Ordinances, all have ſomthing like Chriſt in them, but it is all but ths number of a man, meerly humane, carnall Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, humane gifts, and anointings in ſtead of the Spirit carnall Church, invented Ordinances: but I paſſe it at preſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECTION <hi>II.</hi> What is his Reigne.</head>
               <p>ANtichriſts reign is likewiſe in the ſpirit, and in the Letter; Antichriſt or the man of ſinne, is as high in his reigne, as confident of his good eſtate.</p>
               <p>Firſt his reigne in the ſpirit in the myſtery? he ſheweth himſelfe, that he is God, he perſwades ſoules, that he is the Chriſt, his wiſdom and his righteouſneſſe, his rules and his ordinances, they are of God; and they muſt ſtand, although it hath neither Scripture nor reaſon, I meane in the Spirit, for it: and thus this myſtery of iniquity hath reigned a long time; it began to work in the Apoſtles dayes.</p>
               <p>Secondly the reign of Antichriſt in tſte Letter; he alſo viſibly ſheweth himſelfe, that he is God &amp; muſt be ſubmitted unto, under penaltyes, fines, &amp;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:46231:58"/>impriſonments, bitter ſpeaking againſt the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chrſt, than his Ordinances. And thus he reignes with power, and likewiſe with much confidence; for, ſhe ſitteth as QVEEN, and ſaith, ſhe ſhall ſee no ſorrow, but her ſorrowes will come in one day, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> The diſcovery of Antichriſt.</head>
               <p>THE Revelation of Antichriſt may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, either firſt as he openly and publickly reveales himſelfe to be the Antichriſt by his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and powerful acting as the Chriſt, or above Chriſt: of this the Apoſtle ſpeakes, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may be conſidered, as a myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and ſo revealed by the ſpirit of Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Servants; and ſo the revelation or diſcovery of Antichriſt unto the Saints, ſhall be by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt in the preaching of the Goſpel; as it is a myſtery of iniquity in it ſelfe; ſo it muſt be that hidden wiſdome in a myſtery, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. that muſt diſcover it. Now where the Lord worketh for his diſcovery, hee firſt discovers him to be the Antichriſt; he helps the ſoule to find him out: And then ſecondly, he diſcovers the evill, the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of him he lets the ſoule ſee that it is the greateſt and the ſubtleſt adverſary that ever it
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:46231:58"/>had to deal withall; the moſt dangerous, becauſe clothed under ſo faire and Chriſt-like a Garb, and the hardeſt to be diſcovered; ſuch an adverſary, as bears ſoules in hand that they are going to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven when they are in the broad and rode-way to ruine, like a cunning <hi>Hoc as Poc as,</hi> that jugleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a mans Eſtate before he is awarc of it, and all the while pretends friendſhip, and thus it is the ſpirit of God in the Goſpell, that muſt diſcover and reveale Antihriſt in the myſtery, that ſame ſpirit who revealed it to the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> and the ſame who revealed both his riſing and falling to <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Revelations, thoſe who think to attain the diſcovery of him by humane induſtry, hiſtoricall readings &amp;c. are exceeding low in their apprehenſions and come ſhort of the diſcovery of him: he may be ſtrongly working in a man while he is discovering of him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> What ſhall be the ruine of Antichriſt?</head>
               <p>THe conſumation of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall be by the ſame means that diſcovers him the bright goings forth of Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel: for as the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt goes up in the ſpirit; (for the Kingdome of Heaven is within you &amp;c.) ſo the Kingdome of Antichriſt muſt go down: this
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:46231:59"/>is the meanes fore-told and preſcribed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, who fore-ſaw him in his riſing. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <q>The Lord will conſume him with the breath of his mouth, &amp; deſtroy him with the brightnes of his coming, the preaching of the Goſpel, and the bright comings forth of Jeſus Chriſt in the ſpirits of his people ſhall both conſume &amp; deſtroy him:</q> As it is not a humane wiſdom that ſhall diſcover him, ſo neither is it a humane power that muſt deſtroy him: for all humanity in the things of God; whether wiſdom or power, it is Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: Therefore, not that which ſhall deſtroy Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; but that which will uphold him untill he be deſtroyed: the ruine of Antichriſt is farther held forth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.6. The Angell flyeth through the midſt of heaven, preaching the everlaſting Goſpel; &amp; verſe 8. Another Angel followeth, ſaying, That Babylon, is fallen that great City, &amp;c. The prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel is the means you ſee, of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts ruine: and the Sermon is, feare God, and give glory to him. This Sermon is that will ruine Antichriſt both in the letter and in the ſpirit; <hi>give glory to God,</hi> that is, let God be all, and in all: let God be your enjoyment in the ſpirit; ſee you live upon nothing below him, give not glory to Creatures, duties, actings; any thing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the firſt Adam, or Antichriſt: give glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to God in the Letter, give not glory to man, ſet not up man in the roome of God; do not cry the voice of Man, and not of God, in any of the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:46231:59"/>things of God; and this is the Sermon that ſhall ruine Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>See likewiſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1 2.9. The Divel and Satan, the myſticall Antichriſt, was caſt forth of Heaven, to the earth; that is, he ſhall not be ſuffered any more to delude ſouls, in a heavenly ſhape: the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell is now turned Chriſtian, and he makes warre with the Saints, under the name of Chriſt, both in the Spirit, as well as in the Letter: And hence the great warre is between Chriſt and Satan in Heaven, that is betweene the Heaven of Chriſt, &amp; the Heaven of Satan under the name of Chriſt. But now <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, he ſaw Satan caſt out of Heaven, that is he ſhall deceive ſoules no more, in a Heavenly form: neither perſecute the Saints any more under the name of Chriſt: (A glorious work &amp; it is coming on a pace) for the moſt part of ſouls in that part of the world called Chriſtans are ruined in the Divels heaven, &amp; believe it, this is the great work Chriſt hath to do in theſe latter dayes, the conſumation of Antichriſts, that is, firſt of all, Antichriſts ſpirituall deluſions by which he hath deceived ſoules. 2. And all Antichriſts, delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forms &amp; ordinances by which the common ſort of people are generally deluded: the work of Chriſt is to powre down vials of wrath upon the head of the Man of ſin both in the ſpirit, &amp; in the letter; look about you therefore all you, whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual life conſiſts in nothing, but ſpirituall &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:46231:60"/>deluſions, with invented and Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian formes and Ordinances. A Vial of wrath is coming on you, which will ſhatter to pieces all your confidence, and then if mercy prevent not you may ſtand looking on, and crying; alas elas in one houre is ſo great riches come to naught? and then when this is fulfilled, there ſhall be no more War in Heaven or ſpirituall deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under the name of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>A glorious word for thoſe that dwell in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and that which will cauſe joy to the Saints. For, firſt, they ſhall be without, and above, all danger of deluſions in the ſpirit or in the letter,</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, they ſhal from the ſame ground be for ever freed from fellowship with Hypocrits and literall Chriſtians; for their communion ſhall be more in the ſpirit and leſſe in the Letter, and there ſhall in no wiſe enter into it any thing that defileth, neither whatſoaever worketh abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is, lives earthly carnall, and prophane, or maketh a lye that is, Hypocriticall that ſeems to be what he is not.</p>
               <p>But they which are written in the Lambs book of life: and there ſhall be no more a Canaanite in the houſe of the Lord for ever. This is the great work Chriſt hath to do in theſe latter dayes, the conſumation of the Kingdome of Antichriſt, who hath a long time ſat in his ſeat, with the exaltati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his own Kingdome in the ſpirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:46231:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECTION V. Queſt.</hi> When he ſhall be ruined?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> FIrſt, in the myſtery and ſpirits of the Saints, as Jeſus Chriſt comes in, and ſhines gloriouſly in the ſpirit; ſo ſhall Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt be diſcovered, and deſtroyed: and ſo he hath received a great blow already in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, through the ſhinings in of Jeſus Chriſt in the ſpirit amongſt many of his Saints, ſo that this is the time of Antichriſts ruine, when Jeſus Chriſt comes in; &amp; takes place in the ſpirit of his people, and the Kingdome of Chriſt increaſeth, ſo the Kingdome of Antichriſt decayeth and conſumeth.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Antichriſt ſhall be deſtroyed when the everlaſting Goſpell ſhall be preached; that is, when the Angell flyeth through the middeſt of Heaven preaching the everlaſting Goſpell; that is, when the Miniſters of the Goſpel ſhal come forth with their full, and heavenly diſcoveries of God in the ſpirit, being permitted to preach the Goſpel by the earthly power in all places with liberty: For, much hath been don already by the witneſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſyng in ſack cloth: that is, almoſt always in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a civill perſecution; and much ignorance of the myſtery of the Goſpel, which hath cauſed them to propheſie in ſac-cloth; yet they have had pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to cauſe fire to come from Heaven, as oft as they
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:46231:61"/>pleaſe, burning up all Antichriſtian formes, and invented deluſions: And then, what will be done, think you, when the Miniſters of the Goſpell ſhall come forih in the full and bright diſcoveries of the Goſpel, with liberties here below for the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Antichriſt ſhall be deſtroyed, when the witneſſes have been ſlaine, &amp; laine dead three dayes; (that is a ſhort ſpace) then a tenth part of the City ſhall fall, and the reſt ſhall have their time prolonged; but, for a time &amp; a ſeaſon. The firſt woe is almoſt paſt; behold, a ſecond, and third woe cometh quickly: wait, and it will come apace.</p>
               <p>Thus have I from the light of Truth, with as much brevity as may be, in ſome meaſure, hinted at this Man of ſinne, this myſtery of Iniquity, with his reign, ruine, with the meanes and time.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:46231:61"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
